<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle or godlie admonition, of a learned minister of the Gospel of our sauiour Christ sent to the pastoures of the Flemish Church in Antwerp, (who name themselues of the Confession of Auspurge,) exhorting them to concord with the other ministers of the Gospell. Translated out of French by Geffray Fenton. Here may the christian reader lerne to know what is the true participatio[n] of the body of Christ, &amp; what is the lauful vse of the holy Supper.</title>
            <author>Corro, Antonio del, 1527-1591.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1569</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19362</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5787</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108710</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844366</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844366</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9172</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19362)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9172)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 207:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle or godlie admonition, of a learned minister of the Gospel of our sauiour Christ sent to the pastoures of the Flemish Church in Antwerp, (who name themselues of the Confession of Auspurge,) exhorting them to concord with the other ministers of the Gospell. Translated out of French by Geffray Fenton. Here may the christian reader lerne to know what is the true participatio[n] of the body of Christ, &amp; what is the lauful vse of the holy Supper.</title>
                  <author>Corro, Antonio del, 1527-1591.</author>
                  <author>Fenton, Geoffrey, Sir, 1539?-1608.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 55, [1] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henry Bynneman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1569.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Antonio del Corro.</note>
                  <note>At foot of title: Cum priuilegio.</note>
                  <note>With a final colophon leaf.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A most Christian and godly sermon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Confessio Augustana --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div rend="roman" type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9172:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9172:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> AN EPISTLE or godlie admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of a learned Miniſter of the Goſpel of our Sauiour CHRIST, <hi rend="blackletterType">Sent to the Paſtoures of the Flemiſh Church in <hi rend="italic">Antwerp,</hi> (who name themſelues of the Confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auspurge,)</hi> exhorting them to concord with the other Miniſters of the Goſpell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of French by <hi rend="italic">Geffray Fenton</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here may the chriſtian Reader lerne to know what is the true participatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the body of CHRIST, &amp; what is the lauful vſe of the holy Supper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">PRINTED AT LON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, by Henry Bynneman</hi> ANNO. 1569.</p>
            <p>CVM PRIVILEGIO.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9172:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9172:2"/>
            <head>To the right worshipfull Iohn Byron Eſquier, Geffray Fenton wiſheth a happy new yeare, with a glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome continuance of many.</head>
            <p rend="italic">IN obſeruing (ſir) this laſt yere your order &amp; condition of doing, I founde the cuſtome and courſe of your vertues nothing inferiour to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon opinion of the ſame. Wherof as I proued peculiarly in my ſelf by many means &amp; times, but moſt by a ciuile co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation of your compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie during the best part of the ſommer, ſo I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt my ſelfe no leſſe vnworthy of ſuch benefite paſsed, than vnmete eftſoones to vſe or partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate with the like, if ſuch det be not diſcharged by ſome thankefull argument of good will, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded with matter of myne own indeuor, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the qualitie of my tale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And albeit I haue at tymes heretofore proteſted vnto you ſimply my ſeruiceable &amp; vnfained zeale (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I hope you doubt not) yet me thinkes, with the nature of a barren ſoyle yelding no fruite, the ſame might ſeeme no leſſe vnprofitable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, than imperfecte in my ſelfe, if it be not approued with ſome abſolute and vnfayned ſhewe, and that in the publyke eye of the worlde, in whiche respect I haue preſumed to lay afore you this little Tranſlation, a worke neyther improper for the purpoſe of good doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine,
<pb facs="tcp:9172:3"/> nor impertinent to the profeſsion of a true Christian, and for the mater, it diſcouereth a a most perfect Methode or plot, to diſcerne the principall pointes of our Religion, with certein ſpeciall places of Scripture toward the ende, to induce the church to vnitie, and the people to imbrace the league of charitie left vs by Chriſt as well in the example of himſelfe, enduryng ſundry ſortes of villanous reproches, as in the preſident of his Apostles and Prophetes, who ſuffered with greate pacience the barbarous dispoſition of the enimies to their religion.</p>
            <p rend="italic">This as I culled out amongſt other, as a worke reſembling your owne vertues, ſo in the often reading it, I doute not you ſhall finde a happie confirmation of iudgement in good things, the ſame as the Apostle ſayeth, being one chiefe and principall frute of knowledge, and therfore moſte neceſſarie that we acquaint our myndes with godly exerciſes and meditations of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, praying you lastly to let it receyue youre protection, to the ende our countrey and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian neighboures, by youre meane the rather, may plentifully participate in the benefite of the ſame, wherin alſo I accompt my trauaile ſufficiently aunſwered, if this become thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:9172:3"/> to you, in ſort of an earneſt peny or first of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer of my good will, reſeruing notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to giue a better ſhewe hereafter, as tyme with quiet leyſure ſhall aſsist me. And ſo God giue you a good new yeare, and confirme vs all in his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feare.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At my lodging <date>the tenth of Decembre. 1569.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your ſure frende Geffray Fenton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div rend="blackletterType" type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:9172:4"/>
            <head>A prayer of the Author, for the concorde of doctrine, and vnitie in wils in diuine things, appertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the aduauncement of the Goſpell of CHRIST.</head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">O</hi> Eternall and mercifull Lord, who as thou art God of peace, loue and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, ſo diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions quarels and debates are hatefull vnto thée: We ſée how (with good right) thou chaſtiſeſt oure malice and rebellion ageinſt thée, by the diuerſitie of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions and ſtrange iudgements raigning at this day amongſt men, ſpecially in the cauſe of religion. In the beginning (Lord) thou haſt created man to thyne own image and likeneſſe, to the ende that he and his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie mighte be one thing with thée, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing one only opinion led according to thy holy worde and manifeſtation and one wil affected to embrace that which thou deman deſt, whereupon might folow workes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to thy diuine and holy lawe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9172:4"/>
            <p> But the ſerpent enemie of all peace, and on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie a louer of diſſention and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, taught oure firſt Fathers the leſſon of infidelitie, diſtruſt, preſumption and arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant curioſitie. Alas (our good God and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator) that we feele and make dayly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of miſerable effects of that leſſon prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Sathan in our harts: for euery one of vs ſtriues to be a god vppon earth, euery one pretends to be able, (by the touche of his owne iudgement) to diſcerne whiche is good or euill, what is agreable or inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to thy diuine Maieſtie, yea euery one thinkes to be the maiſter that ought to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct his neighbour. Take pitie of vs (O Lorde) and deface in oure hartes this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe leſſon (full of ambition &amp; pride) make vs vnderſtand in good earneſt, that thou art hée only, to whom belongeth to diſcerne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the good and euill, and betwene the truthe and dreames, and that it is thou lord who by thy eternall worde Ieſus Chriſte, giueſt lighte, manifeſtation, &amp; knowledge of thy ſecretes to thoſe that feare thée: thou art he alone, who by thy holy ſpirit doeſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect &amp; teach thy diſciples, which make them of thy ſchole and worde. Withoute thée
<pb facs="tcp:9172:5"/> (Lorde) wée are loſt and confounded, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thy truthe wée are liers, without thy doctrine we bée falſefiers, without thy inſtruction we bée preſumptuous &amp; proud. Alas, wée, euen wée miſerable creatures, to giue oure ſelues an eſtimation in the world, forſake thy eternall worde, whiche is the trée of euerlaſting life, and go deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the frute of knowledge gyuen by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than: From thence (Lorde) it comes, that our knowledge and wiſdome is accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with pride and arrogant contention, not giuing place one to an other, whereby wée ſhewe that oure wiſdome and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is not from aboue for by the ſame wée faine to ſearche thy glorie, and to bliſſe and prayſe thée as our GOD and Father: and in the meane while, to mainteyne our opinions, wée accurſe men faſhioned to thyne owne Image and likeneſſe, in ſuche ſorte that out of one only mouth procéedes bothe curſſe and bliſſing: a thing whiche might ſéeme both impoſſible and incredible, if dayly experience did not diſcouer theyr manifeſt and abſolute effectes. For howe is it poſſible, that a fountayne ſhould caſte out of one vent or ſpoute, water that is
<pb facs="tcp:9172:5"/> pleaſaunt, and withall bitter and ſalte? Who can beléeue, that a Figge trée can bring forth Olyues, or a Vine yeld Figs? Truly Lorde, ſuch contrarieties are not ſo contrarie in naturall things, as is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in things ſpiritual wherin we deale. For how ſhould men beléeue our wordes, ſaying we loue God, when by our workes we diſcouer a certeyne hate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to our neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours? We ſaye, we ſearch no other thing than the aduauncement of the kingdome of Chriſt, and yet wée afflict and perſecute the very members of Chriſt: We crie with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen throate, that we are of the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours of the holy Goſpell of peace, and yet our attemptes and councels are not but of warres, murders, and effuſions of mans bloud. Oh moſt wretched that we are, we rayſe and lifte vp our handes to praye and call vpon thée, which notwithſtanding are all ſprinkled and goared with the bloud of thoſe whiche thou haddeſt made liuely, by thy wonderfull prouidence.</p>
            <p>Seing that ſuch is our wiſdome, ſprong of oure bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fe, that is to ſay, earthly, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall and diuelliſhe, accompanied with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ute, wrath, trouble, with all workes of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie:
<pb facs="tcp:9172:6"/> giue vs Lorde by thy bountie thy wiſedome from an highe, whiche may be pure, peaceable, moderate, tractable, full of mercie and good frutes, and far from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, diſſentions, and all hipocriſie: bring to paſſe lord, that the frutes of iuſtice may be ſowen in peace for thoſe whiche vſe &amp; make peace, and by thoſe which be the true pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cers and ſhewers of the ſame peace: bring to paſſe Lorde, that we ſhewe our ſelues wiſe and well aduiſed, not onely in vaine wordes and bable of Religion, but let vs bring forth in our conuerſation the frutes of the Goſpell wherein we beléeue, accompanying our faith with workes of humilitie, and celeſtiall wiſdome.</p>
            <p>Take pitie on vs (O Lorde) by thy bountie and mercie, for we confeſſe to haue offended thée greatly and withoute mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and we confeſſe that the rebukes whiche thou ſendeſt vppon vs, are but the iuſte rewardes of our merites. Thou Lord ſuffereſt, that we haue warre, diſſentions, quarelles and debates, and that we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte vnnaturall murder one vppon an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that more for the cauſe of our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular opinions, than in reſpect of zeale to
<pb facs="tcp:9172:6"/> thy glorie, (whereof notwithſtanding we vaunte our ſelues) thou ſendeſt to vs the meſſangers and Heraldes of thy wrathe, that is to ſaye, infections of the aire, conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious diſeaſes, peſtilence, famine, ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracks, with other like arguments of thy heauy diſpleaſure towardes vs, and yet we harden our hartes: thou ſuffereſt that ſtraunge Nations, Barbarous and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters do raiſe them ſelues againſt vs for the ouerthrowe of the Churches and Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies where thy name ought to be glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and wée truſting in our owne forces, induſtries, and frayle wiſdoms, will not haue recourſe to thée, and therefore with good right oh Lorde, thou leaueſt vs to the mercie of the infidelles, and ſuffereſt the ſuperſtitious to haue victorie ouer vs. Oh Father of mercie, beſtowe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs thy piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full eyes, reforme our hartes and oure af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, engraue in vs the only zeale of thy glorie, graffe in our mindes the true trée of life whiche is Ieſus Chriſte our Sauiour and Redéemer, the fruts of whom do make vs liuely: let vs be filled with true fayth, liuely hope, mutual and brotherly charitie, &amp; that we exerciſing in works of true mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification,
<pb facs="tcp:9172:7"/> iuſtice, innocencie and holineſſe, may be in the ende poſſeſſors of the eternal life, for the obteyning whereof we haue bin choſen &amp; predeſtinate to the prayſe of thée, (oh father of mercy, and of thy Chriſt our only ſauiour) to whome with thy holy Spirit be glorie &amp; prayſe for euer.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div rend="blackletterType" type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:9172:7"/>
            <head>A prayer to Ieſus Chriſt, for peace and vnitie in the Church,</head>
            <byline>by Geffray Fenton</byline>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">O</hi> Soueraigne Lorde, who beyng the eternall worde and true GOD with God thy father, didſt take our nature to viſite in forme of man the poore children of Adam, loſt by their infidelitie, diſtruſte, and peruerſe opinion againſt their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. And alſo by thy meane and remedie, haſt efteſones reſtabliſſed the confederati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betwene GOD and vs, approuing the ſame moſt painfully in the mortall mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome of thy moſt innocent body bléeding on the croſſe for the expiacion of our ſinnes: we beſeche thée (oh Sauiour of the world) that euen as thou arte come to conſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mate and confirme our reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciliation, thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt alſo reconcile our hartes, knitte oure wils, and ſende thy ſpirit of truth amongſt vs, to the ende, that we all concurring in one iudgement and opinion, may remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that we are called to bée members of one body, whereof Lord, we acknowledge thée to be the chiefe and ſupreame head, and ſo deteſting inciuill partialities, we may
<pb facs="tcp:9172:8"/> be of one opinion, agrée in one minde, and vſe one mutuall and charitable direction touching the matter of oure Religion. Thou haſt left vnto vs (O Lorde) the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of thy holly Supper, as a memortal of oure communion and ſpirituall vnitie with thée, and alſo to inſtructe vs in ſuche lawes of charitie, as ought to be of famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar conuerſation amongeſt vs all. And yet we (ſuch is the nature of our fragilitie and condition of our vnworthineſſe) as we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the excellent benefite of that moſt high fauour, ſéeing that in place to tye and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne our ſelues with thée, we doe more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraunge vs from thée, and that by reaſon of our quarelles and queſtions of contention: In place to conſider that we are one bodie, one churche, and one bread made of ſundrie graines, we ſhewe our ſelues proude, and giue ſundrie proues of our ambition in ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to eſtabliſhe a ſpeciall eſtimation of our peculiar and priuat opinions: in hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling very often thy preſence in thy holly Supper by ſubtill diſputation, we become farre from thy true and liuely preſence, in contending whether the ſinners &amp; vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full may communicate thy body, we make
<pb facs="tcp:9172:8"/> our ſelues ſinners and incapable to receyue and enioye thy benefites: laſtly and in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, oh Lord, our zeale is ſo indiſcrete, that in ſtryuing to enterteyne the puritie of the doctrine of fayth, we breake the league and lawe of charitie, yea &amp; in perſecuting with rebuke ſuch as we accompt to be heretikes in the doctrine of fayth: our malice, with want of diſcretion makes vs ſéeme tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natured into heretikes of charitie, corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the meanes of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly vnitie.</p>
            <p>I beſeche thée therfore (oh ſonne of God) let thy gracious pitie fall vppon vs, and ſo open the eyes of our vnderſtanding, as we may diſcerne the true frute of thy holy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ordinance, take from amongeſt vs all ſectes and varieties of opinions, and reduce vs at laſt to the obedience of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and only worde: reueale vnto vs thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirite with this priuilege of grace, that by hys vertue he may drawe vs all into one corporation and bodye, whereof thou (O Lord) mayeſt be heade, and lette him breath into vs ſtrengthe and power to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuer in workes of true Iuſtice, innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and holyneſſe, duryng oure courſe
<pb facs="tcp:9172:9"/> in this tragical and miſerable pilgrimage, and in the ende let (we beſéeche thee) the ſame holy ſpirite tranſlate vs into the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, (purchaſed to our vſes by the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice and oblation of thy moſt precious death) wherin thou raigneſt now glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly with the Father and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſte, and there ſhall remayne infinitely.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div rend="blackletterType" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:9172:9"/>
            <head>To my moſt dearely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued in our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, the only Redéemer and aduocate of men towards the heauenly Father, my brother Ministers and Paſtors in the church of <hi rend="italic">Antwerp,</hi> namyng them ſelues of the Churche of <hi rend="italic">Auspurge,</hi> Grace and peace from God and his Sonne IESV CHRIST, to the ende, that by the bond of his holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, we may al be knit in the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and Confeſsion of the Goſpel of Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T my firste</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to this town of <hi rend="italic">Antwerpe</hi> (ryght ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable in Chriſt) and that at the requeſt of certeine the Faithfull there, I found cauſe of ſingular comforte in the view of the wonderfull woork rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp by the Lorde, by meane of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and that in ſo ſhorte tyme, as ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to ſuche as haue aſſiſted it, it maye ſéeme no leſſe impoſſible than incredible. For if we wonder in certeine Trées and
<pb facs="tcp:9172:10"/> Fruits, who ſometimes yeld encreaſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue cuſtome, or againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon courſe of Nature, as though the Lorde were of purpoſe to releue and reſtore ſome coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey afflicted with hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger: what may we ſay of theſe ſpirituall plantes whiche the Father of mercy ſo ſodeinly and ageynſt al hope of man, hath ſet and planted in theſe Low countreys, &amp; ſpecially in this citie of <hi rend="italic">Antwerpe?</hi> Truly we are bound to acknowledge it as a worke of ſtrange maruell of our God, and to ſay with the prophet, this incredible encreaſe hath bin made by the Lord, whom we find worthy of admiration in our eyes: it is the right hand of God which hath reueled his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: it is the right hand of God that hath exalted vs: it is the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of God that hath manifeſted his power, we ſhall not die at al, but we ſhal liue to declare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord: wherin as I entred more déeply into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> view &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of theſe things, ſo I thought it alſo an office and duetie in mée to crie with the ſayde Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet: Confirme Lord, and aduaunce the woorke thou haſte begon in vs: buyld vp
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:9172:10"/> ageyne the walles of thy holy temple: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the ruines of thy Heauenly <hi rend="italic">Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> to the end that the Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the earth may come to doo thée ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and offer preſentes: gather toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther agein O God, the diſperſed of <hi rend="italic">Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 This was the cauſe wherin I reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for certeyn dayes with glad continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, till vpon further viewe of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of eſtate within the citie, I found oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to conuert my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t intoo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceites of ſorowe, as ſéeing on euery ſyde with what diligence Sathan laboured to hinder the aduauncement of this church, not only by means of open enemies, but alſo by the indiſcretion &amp; want of regard in ſuch as name themſelues maiſter Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the houſe of God: for ſuch as fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red God and wiſhed a publication of his glory, cried out &amp; exclamed that the chair of truth was becom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chaire of diſſentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſeruing no more as a pulpit to preach Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the appeaſor of troubled co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, to pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce an vnitie, a brotherly charity, nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mortificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old Adam, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked motions of concupiſcence,
<pb facs="tcp:9172:11"/> but rather it was vſed as a place of inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiues, &amp; iniuries, with wordes of malice <note place="margin">In the Pulpit oughte not be preached other words than of God, to know &amp; ſerue Chriſt.</note> tending to a mutual hate of one towards another, &amp; diſſention of doctrine, wherin vpon inquirie of ſuch fault, with the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance &amp; authors of the ſame, I fynd your ſyde not leaſt giltie, as being ſuche amongeſt you, who in open aſſemblie, with woords and libels of malice, are not aſhamed to cal the other Miniſters of the Goſpel, Heretikes, Sacramentaries, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels ageynſt the ſtate, &amp; people vnwoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of place in the common wealth, with other words improper for the maieſty of ſuch a place, which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrated purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to teach the word and will of our God.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Now (brethren) if ſuch or ſuch lyke matter of reproche ſhould be pronounced in the Pulpit of certein Moonks or mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Friers, the very organs of the <hi rend="italic">Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine</hi> Antechriſt, ſent of their ſuppoſtes to trouble the church of Chriſt, to darken his glory, and reſiſt the aduancement of his kingdome, we woulde endure them with pacience, as knowyng well inough y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch ſort of Prophetes be the diſciples
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:9172:11"/> of <hi rend="roman">Balaam,</hi> who ſell theyr tongs to curſe the people of God, yea ſomtimes agaynſt the ſenſe of their propre conſcience: wée aſſure our ſelues that the mouth of ſuche hypocrites ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not bring foorth other than woordes of infection and full of taſt of all euill: for they as they are painted ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres, ſo canne they not vomit vp other <note place="margin">Deſcription of the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the Papiſtes.</note> matter than ſuche as is couertly couched within, that is to ſay, all infection and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyneſſe: And we are moſt certeine, that thoſe kinde of people bequeathed to <hi rend="roman">Baall</hi> and contentement of theyr bellie, ſéeing the fal of their Marmit by litle and litle, will enforce them ſelues to exclaime a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt them that diſcouer theyr abuſes, hypocriſies, and villanous trumperies: wee beléeue alſo that ſuche ſuppoſtes of Sathan, who from the begynnyng hath bin the Authour of diſſention, a louer of murder (with deſire of effuſion of bloud) wil labor in the imitation of their father and maiſter, and that (vnder the pretence of the Goſpell) they will proclaime ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; trouble, and as the Prophet ſayth, vomite furious matter agaynſt ſuche as
<pb facs="tcp:9172:12"/> ſtuffe not their bellies according to their fanſies and faſhions of cuſtome: of ſuche ſorte of railers wée receyue no greate care, ſéeing wée are not ignoraunt with what iudgement and puniſhement, God will viſite them though hée be long: for they be of that ſorte of whome the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi rend="roman">Iude</hi> ſpeaketh in his Epiſtle catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke, as vpon whom euill ſhall happen, <note place="margin">Reade the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle of S. Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle.</note> for they followe the trayn of <hi rend="roman">Cain:</hi> they aba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den them ſelues into the error of the hyer of <hi rend="roman">Baalam,</hi> they ſhall periſhe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the contradiction of <hi rend="roman">Corus.</hi> They are ſtained at the Banket of the charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Faythfull, feedyng them ſelues without feare: they are cloudes without water, caried away with euery wynde: they be trées whoſe fruite is rotten, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted and of no commoditie, twice dead, once by the vniuerſall corruption of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, wherewith all men be ſtained, and the other by the death of theyr Monkery, with the whiche they haue dedicated to <hi rend="roman">Baal</hi> their bodies and theyr ſeruices: they be ragyng waues of the ſea, ſkumming their villanies: errant ſtarres for whom
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:9172:12"/> is prepared the ſhaddowes of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng darkeneſſe: They are murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, quarellers, walkyng accordyng to theyr couetouſneſſe, theyr mouthes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing words of venomous ſubſtance, and louing men onely for their profite. They incenſe diuiſyons, and are peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of ſenſualitie, impartyng nothyng with the Spirite: They are the very paynter and portraite whiche the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaketh of in ſuche ſorte of Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers. And therefore doe wée eſtéeme of them as they deſerue, not fearyng any harm they can do to the troupe or felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip electe of God, for they diſcouer ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently their poyſon and the leuyn of the Phariſeys.</p>
            <p n="4">4 But touchyng you (deare and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable brethren) one woorde procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from your mouth pierceth the heart, and giueth vs cauſe of ſingular ſorrow, with feare leaſt the ſame ſtirre vp ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the flocke of Ieſus Chriſte: And wo be to hym that ſhall bée the cauſe of ſuche ſlaunder ageynſt one of the leaſt, it were better that ſuch a one had faſtned
<pb facs="tcp:9172:13"/> to his necke a great Mylnſtone and caſt into the bottom of the ſea, than to be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to offende and put diſſention in the church, which the Lord begins to noriſh in this towne, and who now being in hir cradle, is in more neceſſitie to be fed with the true woord of god, releued in hir affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and comforted in hir perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, than to be diſquieted with ſubtil and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious queſtions, diuiſions and debates vpon the matter of our confeſſion: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in as we both féele and ſée the wonderful benefits which the Lord hath layde both vpon you and vs, hauing drawne vs out of the miſerable quagmier and mariſh of ſuperſtition and idolatrie amongeſt the Papiſts, ſo let vs wiſh (that as true Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God) we may employ our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues with one accord to ſet foorth the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <note place="margin">A mean to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng the doctrine.</note> of him, who of priſoners of darkneſſe, hathe made vs happie members of his moſte cléere lyght. If there be any thing which you iudge not well vnderſtanded of vs, were it not better to come to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with vs, or vſe brotherly admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, than to exclaime in the Pulpit,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:9172:13"/> and fill the Bookebinders ſhoppes with Inuectiues and Apologies of ſpite? were it not better (with inuocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord) to entertaine quietly the affai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of the aduauncement of his glorie, than to leuie warre againſt oure ſelues with the ſhot of the pen, whoſe wounds are farre more daungerous and incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, than the ſmitings eyther of the bow or croſbowe: bicauſe the one offends but <note place="margin">Warre of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men moſt ſlaunderous.</note> the body and fleſh, and the other pierceth both depely and bloudily the renoume of the perſon, whiche euery one holdeth in value more deare and precious than ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther golde or ſiluer, with all the riches in the worlde.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Alas miſerable and wretched that we are, what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnation, what iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment do we heape vpon our heads when we preach to the Souldiers to lay away their armes and forbeare to offend com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealths, and wée, euen we our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, doo carie in our Inkhorns weapons moſt ſharpe, with arrowes of poyſon to thunder vpon ſuch as doo not offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues wholly to our aduiſe and opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,
<pb facs="tcp:9172:14"/> and refuſe to hazarde theyr Faythe in the interpretations whiche wee make of Gods woorde?</p>
            <p n="6">6 Thys arrogante ouerwéenyng is <note place="margin">Whereof it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that the audience in the reformed church bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</note> the cauſe why the Lorde ſuffereth that the frute of oure preachyngs is eyther none at all, or at leaſt of ſo little effect, that oure Audience in theyr lyfe and conuerſation, doo declare what ſlender knowledge and feare of GOD they learne by oure Exhortations. God ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth alſo to fall vppon vs Inquiſitours and Perſecutoures in the verye ſame ſorte, that wée preſume to bee the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the Faythe of others. And by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wée wyll rule all the worlde by the touche of the Sentence and aduiſe of this or that man, the Lorde incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the very Children them ſelues to calle vs Parciall Sectatoures, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miratours of the opynions of men, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng ſome Martiniſtes, ſome Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtes, ſome Ozeandrines, ſome Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthonyſtes, and ſome Brentiens, wyth diuers other like names, and that with good ryghte: bycauſe wée haue not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:9172:14"/> oure eyes fixed on the onely aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of the glorie of Ieſus Chryſte and his Churche, whyche is Catholike and vniuerſall: But euery one wyll deale aparte, euery one entice and drawe hys audience aparte, euery one maynteyne the renoume of his inſtitutour, and that which woorſe is, euery one as ſupreame Iudge giues ſentence of condemnation without appeale ageynſt others.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Of thys myſerable cauſe it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe, that this Churche béeing at this day deliuered from the inſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table inquiſition and tyranny of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes, and that by the grace of GOD, and goodneſſe of oure Kyng and Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Magiſtrate, wée haue notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding amongeſt oure ſelues ſupreme inquiſitors, who with an arrogancie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the Phariſies call the other doggs, and worldlings, not conſidering belike, (ſuch is their arrogancie) that this word worldlyng, or of the worlde, carryeth wyth it an vnreuerent ſpyte to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſte, according to that he hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf doth ſay, that the world is his enimie,
<pb facs="tcp:9172:15"/> and that he wil not pray for it: Al which condemnation is founded vpon that that the worldlings (as they call them) will not accommodate themſelues to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Sacraments in their faſhion, nor floriſh in imaginations and queſtions of ſubtiltie, but are contented in the ſimplicitie of the woorde of God, with direction of the holy Spirite to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct their conſciences.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Other there be who of their confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Catechiſmes, Commentaries, and traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, make as it were a fifth goſpel, giuing no leſſe authoritie to their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular interpretations, than if they were of the Articles of Faith, not refuſyng to call all them heretikes, who poynte by poynt doo not folow their imaginations, whiche although were good and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall to edifie, yet are they none other tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the breath of men, and therefore vnwoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon with the eternall woord.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Theſe things (Brethren) with the conſideration of them mouyng no ſmall ſorow in my mind, foreſeing (as it were) the breach whiche Sathan myght make
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:9172:15"/> in the houſe and troupe of God by ſuch a mean, procured me to attempt familiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one of your brethren and companions in the woork of God, who as he ſéemed of ſome ſuperintendence and authoritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, ſo I imparted with him the <note place="margin">M. Yllyryc.</note> great ſlaunder growyng to the neighbor churches thereabout by ſuche differences and diſſentions manifeſtly publiſhed, not only by bookes of infamie, but alſo in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurious inuectiues, in open aſſemblies, whome I requeſted in the name of the Lorde, to exhorte his companions to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare their further procéedings in ſuche ſort, with diſcontinuance of their ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous order of dooings, altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of the miniſterie of Chryſt.</p>
            <p n="10">10 His anſwer hereuntoo argued his ſufficient forwardneſſe, complaining al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit ageynſt others, and ſaying that the beſt meane for accorde, were to bryng in diſputation, and to ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dle chiefly the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion vpon the Lordes Supper, vpon the diuers and ſundry conſtruction whereof, ſprong bothe the diſorder and diſſention: I ſayd there was ſlender hope of preſent
<pb facs="tcp:9172:16"/> accorde this way, if bothe the one and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would not diſclaime their ſtout and ſtraunge order in proponing their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and interpretations: For (ſayde I) if they obſerue no more modeſtie in their woordes than they haue vſed temperance in their bookes and wrytyngs, neyther can the cauſe bée determined, nor the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure reduced, for whiche reſpecte I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it not out of purpoſe to take a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Fayth, and imparte with the people thoſe Articles wherein wée all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée, leauing the reſte that maye bring likelyhood of diſſention or ſlaunder to the Church.</p>
            <p n="11">11 Herein hée ſéemed to aprpoue my aduiſe, with perſuaſion that to take the Confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auſpurge</hi> were moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarye to enforce thys accorde, ſubſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng ſuche Articles, as with good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience wée myghte receyue, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete the other accordyng to oure vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, which wée haue already doone, with meaning to bring them to light to the edification of the Church, to the ende euery one may ſée that the controuerſy is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:9172:16"/> not ſo greate as is giuen oute to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who being bothe troubled and ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with ſuche diuerſities, knoweth not what pathe to treade, hearyng ſome preache that Chriſte is here, and other ſaye hée is not there, but here: The Churche of Chryſte is not ſuche one, but oures is the right Churche: wée are of <hi rend="roman">Paule,</hi> and they bée of <hi rend="roman">Cephas,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of <hi rend="roman">Apollo.</hi> Alas are wee baptiſed eyther in the name of <hi rend="roman">Paule, Iohn,</hi> or <hi rend="roman">Martine?</hi> Is not onely Ieſus Chryſt our Redéemer? Is it not in hys name that wée are baptized and broughte into the Churche? Is not hee the ſouerayne Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toure, graduated not at <hi rend="italic">Paris,</hi> but in <hi rend="italic">Paradyſe,</hi> whome our Heauenly Father hath ordeyned for our chief ſchoolemaſter with expreſſe commaundement, to heare him? Why then doo wée ſeeke ſo many mayſters and forgers of Doctrine? To conclude, I deſired the ſayde Miniſter to abſteyne from iniurious inuectiues and words of quarel in bookes, with exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his companions to modeſtie and ſéemely temperance in their prechyngs:
<pb facs="tcp:9172:17"/> alſo to perſuade the people to faith, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification and brotherly charitie: whiche albeit, they haue not obſerued, but rather in the contrary haue vſed words of ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the very Pulpit, teaching by that mean their audience to imitate their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders: And which woorſe is, you other my brethren, euen of late haue cauſed to be imprinted certein Libels, wherin you haue reuerſed the names of perſons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and by conuerſion and change of letters haue moſt iniuriouſly handled a certeyn mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpel, calling him a brand of hell, or ſuch lyke name of reproch, a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie farre vnworthy your vocation.</p>
            <p n="12">12 If theſe matters growe to continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, it is not to be douted (good brethren) that the iudgement of God wil not thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vpon our heads, when (beléeue mée) the liuing God will know how &amp; where to finde vs, though we be vnder the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of greate Princes, for the Lorde will not leaue vnpuniſhed ſuche inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis and miſtakings of his deare Church, the whiche as hée hath boughte with his bloud and deliuered from the tirannie of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:9172:17"/> Antechriſt, ſo now ſuch people would eft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoones ſuppeditate and perſecute hir, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour of pietie and inſtruction of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein perſons, whom the Lord hath ſtirred vp to miniſter and ſerue in his temple. And to ſpeake more cléerely in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, knowe yée (good brethren) that tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng <hi rend="roman">Martine Luther, Phillip Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthon,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The authoriti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Luther and other Doctors of the goſpell</note> with other like men, wée eſtéeme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> true ſeruants of god, to whom as the holy ſpirit hath plentyfully imparted his giftes and graces, ſo haue they laboured with an erneſt care both to impugne the abuſes crept into our chriſtian religion, and alſo to manifeſt the truth of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Chryſt: albeit we muſt and do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge them to be no more than me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſo by conſequence ſubiect to be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in many things: for ſo God vſeth to beſtow his giftes and graces vpon men, as the condition of their ignorant nature may ſhew that they bée not Gods vppon earth.</p>
            <p n="13">13 Beſides that, it hapneth many ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, that the ſeruants of God do obſerue a certein ſpecial wiſdom, as not willing
<pb facs="tcp:9172:18"/> to reueale all they do vnderſtande, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng theyr audience not to bée as yet ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of ſuche Doctryne, the ſame hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penyng <note place="margin">The wiſdome of S. Peter.</note> euen to Saincte Peter the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of Chryſte, who albéeit hadde recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued viſybly the holy Spirite, yet hée e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtéemed the tyme not yet conuenyent to manyfeſt to the Iewes the abolition of the Lawe, fearyng leaſte by ſuche a meane the Preachynge of the Goſpell ſhoulde be broughte in contempte, and the publication of the ſame hyndered. On the contrarie, Saincte Paule was of opynion, that in a matter of ſo greate <note place="margin">The zeale of S. Paule.</note> importaunce oughte to bee no dreade of daunger, but to make open and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke manyfeſtation of the lybertie, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Galath.</hi> 2.</note> the Lorde hadde broughte vnto hys Churche. In lyke ſorte wée haue rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to preſume, that theſe good ſeruants of GOD, <hi rend="roman">Luther</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Melancthon,</hi> ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng the greate reſyſtaunce of the worlde ageynſt the preachyng of the pure doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne, and the abolition of the Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes abuſes, iudged it an acte of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:9172:18"/> to gyue a little place too ſuche fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the tyme, and to gayne the heartes of the people gently wythoute makynge them Straungers to the Doctrine of the Sacramentes, wyth expectation from daye too daye of more proper and fytte <note place="margin">Reade the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon to Luther, but chiefly the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</note> occaſyon to reſtore and bryng in whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the true exercyſe and vnderſtanding of the holy Ceremonyes, wherein wée maye bee confyrmed by the procéedings and degrées of the Doctryne whych wée doe ſee in the Bookes of the ſayde holye <note place="margin">Reade the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Sleidans hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye.</note> men. For who can denye that <hi rend="roman">Martine Luther</hi> was ignoraunte in many thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges at hys begynning to preache, which the Lorde reuealed vnto hym after, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrmynge in the woordes of his owne mouth, that GOD hadde ſent hym, not ſo muche to edifie and reeſtablyſhe the Churche of Chriſte, as to ruinate and batter the kingdom of Antechriſt, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he found dayly ſuch chaunge of abuſes vnworthy to be ſupported in the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Religion, that in the ende hée proteſted that the Maſſe deſerued to be aboliſhed, whiche <hi rend="roman">Melancthon</hi> in the ende of the
<pb facs="tcp:9172:19"/> confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auspurge,</hi> mainteyned con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily, profeſſing the Maſſe to be yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in their Churches. All this not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, you (my brethren) of this time, will not as farre as I fynde, agrée that the Maſſe is yet reteyned in youre churches, no not in the ſort that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auſpurge</hi> propoundeth it: The words of <hi rend="roman">Melancthon</hi> be theſe: <hi rend="italic">Falſò ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſantur eccleſiae nostrae, quòd Miſsam abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leant: Retinetur enim Miſſa apud nos, &amp; ſumma Reuerentia celebratur, ſeruantur et vſitatae Ceremoniae ferè omnes, praeterquam quod latinis cancionibus admiſcentur alicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi Germanicae, quae additae ſunt ad docendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> populum,</hi> that is to ſay: Our churches be falſly accuſed in that they aboliſhe the Maſſe, for the Maſſe is reteined with vs, and is celebrated with greate reuerence, with an vſe and obſeruation of almoſt al <note place="margin">What Supper the Proteſtants had in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</note> the accuſtomed ceremonies, ſauing that in ſome places there be certen Canticles in the Dutche, entermedled with thoſe that are ſoong in the Latine, and that to teache the people.</p>
            <p n="14">14 Sée (brethren) how you wold now
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:9172:19"/> aduow ſo goodly a reformation of Maſſe, being aſſured that ſuch inſtitution is the true heape of vanities inuented by men, and tending to the prophanation and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolition of the holy Supper of the Lord: but if others in the very time of <hi rend="roman">Luther</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Melancthon,</hi> haue bin moued wyth the ſpirite of God, and with a zeale of S. Paule haue reſiſted ſuch ſimulation (wel affected notwithſtanding to the glorie of God) proueth it therfore in vs any dutie of obſeruation of ſuche Ceremonies, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing regard only to the authoritie of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? God defend. No, let Peter remaine ſtill as Peter, and Martine as Martine, that is to ſay, as a man that may fayle, and let the ſpirite of God be encreaſed by the organs &amp; inſtruments which he ſhall ſtirre vp to manifeſt the truth of his goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, whether he be Paul or <hi rend="roman">Zwinglius,</hi> or <hi rend="roman">Oecolampadius,</hi> or any other of leſſe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie than they. And for oure partes, ſuch organs &amp; inſtruments of God, let vs receiue, honour, and haue in ſingular co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, without perſuaſion or beléef that they be innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or that they can not
<pb facs="tcp:9172:20"/> erre, or that they bée not ignoraunt of ſome things. Let vs beléeue, that from day to day our Lorde wyll ſtirre vp ſuch lyke organs and inſtruments to aduance hys glorie, and to augment the lyghte of his holy Truth, if our owne vnthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe bee not a barre to ſuche liberalitie begon by our GOD.</p>
            <p n="15">15 Beſydes (brethren) I conſider the lamentable tyme, wherein thoſe holy men dydde liue, as béeing employed ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to purge and clenſe the fylthyneſſe of Papiſtrie, than to ſtudie or conſyder of the introduction of the pure Truthe: they were rather vſed in the reſiſtaunce of the furie of Antechriſte and his ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtes, to flée from one coaſt to an other, to make Apologies and defences, to aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the falſehodes that were layde vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them by dyuers, and to diſpute wyth the monſtrous Moonkes of their Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie and Rogations, than that they had leyſure and quiet libertie to ſearche by meditation the truth of the chriſtian doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine manyfeſted in the diuine word. By which occaſion it came to paſſe, that their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:9172:20"/> writings were ſtuffed with ſo many op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious and ſpiteful woords vnworthy of the true ſeruaunts of God, and perfect pronouncers of the goſpel of peace, which notwithſtanding as we ſupport ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, as hauing regard to ſo wicked a time: So now that God hath ſent vs ſo many beames of his light, let vs leaue to liue &amp; remaine ſo blind as in times paſt.</p>
            <p n="16">16 My meaning (deare brethren) in al this diſcourſe, hath not bin to other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe than to declare the ſmal occaſion we haue aſwel one as another, to make gods or (to ſay more truly) idols of our doctors, &amp; by their occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to entertein vs in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialities, diſſentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; debates vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of our doctrine, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great ſlaunder of the poore &amp; weake co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences &amp; notable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of the propagation of the church: wherin if the <hi rend="italic">Corinthians</hi> haue bin rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked bycauſe they made Partialities to maintein the renoume of S. Paule, the choſen veſſell of GOD, Apoſtle of Ieſus Chryſte, Doctoure of the Gentiles, and to ſpeake in one woorde, a man indued with moſt ſingular and excellent giftes,
<pb facs="tcp:9172:21"/> howe may God laye it ageynſt vs, who contende, quarel, make continual warre, and (as a man wold ſay) deuoure one an other as Dogges and Cats, breaking al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the bonde of charitie, whiche Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt hath left of ſuche eſtimation?</p>
            <p n="17">17 When the Lord would marke his diſciples and childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his father, he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them not to followe the confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auſpurge,</hi> nor the Catechiſme of <hi rend="roman">Martin</hi> or of <hi rend="roman">Iohn,</hi> but he ſayth: In this men ſhal <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">The marke of the chriſtians. Iohn.</hi> 13.</note> know you are my diſciples, if ye loue one other: Alas moſte blinde and myſerable that wée are, whileſt wée diſpute of the true or falſe interpretation of the words of the Sacrament of vnitie, wée breake the very vnitie it ſelfe: in contendyng whether the wicked, infidell, and vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy receyue as well the body of Chryſte in the Supper, as the children of GOD, wée diſfurniſhe oure ſelues of the very Chriſt, and make our ſelues of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them that receyue him not at all: in ſerching whether Chriſt come in fleſh, in Spirite, or in Sacramente, we do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue our ſelues of the true communion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:9172:21"/> of Chriſt: for he that hateth his brother, Chryſte dwelleth not in him: in ſiftyng curiouſly whether the body of Chriſt bee giuen to vs in the bread, vnder the bread, or with the bread, we cut oure ſelues off from the true body of Chriſte, and make vs members of Sathan, the father of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions, quarelles, contentions and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates.</p>
            <p n="18">18 And for my opinion vpon the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the holie Supper, I will ſaye in few woordes (good brethren) what I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande, leauing to euery one his liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to folow that which God ſhall teache him. Wée know right well, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our redeemer Ieſus comming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this worlde, was to manyfeſt to men the good will of his heauenly Father to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes them: and how his Diuine maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie had prouided to remedie the faulte, tranſgreſſion and diſobedience of the firſt <note place="margin">Doctrin of the holy Supper of Chriſt.</note> Adam, by the innocencie, moſte pure iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and obedience ſatiſfactorie of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde and heauenly Adam. And that men mighte be deliuered of the ire and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, putting themſelues vnder
<pb facs="tcp:9172:22"/> the wyngs and couerture of thys So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerayne and eternall Sacrificatour. And <note place="margin">The ſumme of the doctrine of Chryſt.</note> for as muche as the Diuine woorde doth ſhewe vnto vs the malediction of men and tranſgreſſion ageynſte the wyll of GOD, by woordes taken of our corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall nouriture, ſaying, that as man hath eaten the frute of a tree defended hym by his Creatoure, and that by meane of the ſame eatyng, he hath made hymſelfe enimie of the Lorde: In lyke maner Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte oure Redéemer declareth to vs by ſimilitude of eating and drinkyng, the Reconciliation towardes GOD, that his obedience hath brought vs, as if he woulde cléerely ſay, that Man hauing eaten of a forbidden Fruite, hathe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed malediction, where as in eatyng nowe of a fruite giuen him by the hande of GOD, bée hath woonne benediction. The fruite and Trée of life whiche wee oughte to eate, is euen very hée whiche <note place="margin">Chryſt is the Frute of the Tree of life.</note> bryngeth vs ſuche happie newes, who wyth hys vertue and power iudicible, is ſo tyed and ioyned wyth vs by the meane of Faithe and bonde of his holy
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:9172:22"/> Spirite, that he entertaineth our ſoules in ſpirituall and heauenly lyfe, euen as the bread and wyne nouriſheth our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in corporall lyfe.</p>
            <p n="20">20 Vſyng this ſimilitude the Lorde ſayeth in the ſixth of Saint Iohn, that he hym ſelfe is the breade of lyfe, and gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing lyfe, which is deſcended from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and that who eateth of this breade ſhall liue eternally: That is to ſay, hee ſhall eſcape the Curſſe gotten by ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng of the Fruite defended. Hée ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth alſo that hys fleſh is the true meate, and hys bloud the true drinke: And hée that eateth his fleſhe and drynketh his bloud, dwelleth in Chryſte, and Chryſte in hym, who is oure ſeconde and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">The trew vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the words of Chryſt. Iohn.</hi> 6.</note> Adam, within whoſe bodie it is neceſſarie wée bée incorporated, or that hée incorporate hym ſelfe in vs, to the ende that wée maye be able to appeare before GOD, couered with the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell of his moſte innocente fleſhe full of all Iuſtice.</p>
            <p n="21">21 And bycauſe our nature is moſt dul and farre from the true vnderſtanding of
<pb facs="tcp:9172:23"/> theſe myſteries, oure Redéemer Ieſus <note place="margin">Cauſe of the celebration &amp; inſtitution of the Supper.</note> is not only content to propounde vnto vs the coniunction which wée ought to haue with him, by theſe ſimilitudes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons of eating and drinking, but alſo hath ſoughte to ſhewe vs by ſome viſible Ceremonie, the very ſame thing that hée hath taught vs by worde, to the end that not only our eares myght receyue the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of his preaching, but alſo oure eyes féede of ſome viſible repreſentation of that which we ought to be in Chryſte, and Chryſte in vs, that is to ſay, that wée be members of him, nouriſhed with hys proper vertue, and that hée hymſelfe is our foode.</p>
            <p n="22">22 Too this ende (I beleue) that oure ſoueraine doctour Ieſus Chryſte, after he had ſupped with his Diſciples, and cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated the ceremonie of the Paſcal lamb according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, to ſhew vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and all the Churche to come, a liuely repreſentation of the coniunction whiche hée tooke with his membres by meane of the ſacrifice of his death, reſurrection and glorification: He tooke bread, and hauing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:9172:23"/> giuen thanks to God his father, he brake it, and diſtributed it to his Diſciples, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Take, eate, this is my bodie whiche is deliuered for you: And after hée tooke the cuppe and ſayd: This is the cuppe of the new Teſtament, take and drink you all, and doo this in memorie of mée: that is as much as if he ſhoulde ſay, to the end you vnderſtand what I am on youre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, what remedie I bryng vnto you, <note place="margin">Interpretation of the wordes of Chriſte in the Supper.</note> what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iunction it is neceſſarie you haue with me, and I with you: knowe ye that I am bread broken, offered, and ſacrifiſed for the ſatiſfaction of your ſinnes, whiche bread as I am my ſelfe, ſo it is néedefull that it be in you, and giue you heauenly nouriture euen as the materiall breade giues you corporall reléef. And touching the Cup, vnderſtande you, that the ſame doth ſhew you the newe Teſtament and confederation which I practiſe with you, the which teſtament ſhalbe ratified with my bloud, and doo this in memory of me: that is to ſay, when you ſhall breake the breade, as I do, haue remembraunce that you certifie and aſſure youre ſelues that
<pb facs="tcp:9172:24"/> you bée myne, and I am youres, yea youres in ſuche ſorte, as the breade is youres whiche you breake, eate, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſte, and the Wyne whiche giueth you nouriture.</p>
            <p n="23">23 Nowe (brethren) I beſéeche you in the name of our redemer Ieſus, conſider without affection, if the interpretation of this holy Ceremonie and of theſe woords be true or not: If it bée true, to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe do we ſearche ſo many queſtions, ſo many ſubtilties, ſo many vbiquities, with other lyke inuentions to entertain the world in blyndeneſſe? To what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe do we trouble the people with viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ceremonies, with perſuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by that meane they may receiue Ieſus Chriſte? We leaue behind vs, alas, &amp; (as it were) altogither buried, the doctrin of penance, Iuſtification, regeneration, Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, mortification of the old Adam, &amp; cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie <note place="margin">The ſpirit of god is not lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</note> of one to an other, things moſte im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant and neceſſarie, and in the meane while we employ and beſtow our ſelues and time in the interpretation of certein ceremonies, without the which, god is of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:9172:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> power to ſhewe vs that whiche they doe teach vs. We know alſo that many holy men be deceaſed very deuoutly, hauing receyued Chryſt, without receyuing the externall ſignes &amp; viſible elements of the ſupper. And to what ende would it ſerue <note place="margin">The receuing of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſerue nothing to ſuch as will not receiue Chryſt.</note> me to eate all the bread which is in <hi rend="italic">Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne,</hi> giuen by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hands of the miniſters with the words of the ſupper of Chriſt, if I haue not experienced my renuyng, if I haue not taſted my regeneration, if I be not certified that God hath reconciled me with him &amp; receyued me to his mercy, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by ſuche féeling or taſte I do not aſſure my ſelfe to haue receyued Ieſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p n="24">24 This is the doctrine, this (ſay I) is the preaching which we ought to preach and repreache, repeate, and remember alwayes to the people, reſtore to the myndes of the ignorant, and propounde to thoſe that come to learne of vs, not by the ſubtilties of the right hande of God, vbiquities, and ſuche like imaginations. This is a thing very miſerable in oure tyme, that thoſe which ſpeake of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of Ieſus Chriſte, be ſuche as
<pb facs="tcp:9172:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:9172:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9172:26"/> leaſt proue ſuch a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, a thing to bée ſéene by their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, for they ſpeake of Ieſus Chryſte, either ſhut within an armorie, or enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in paſt within bread, vnder the bread, or with the breade, or from vs by .xiiij. or xv. thouſand iorneys, as though the true Temple of Ieſus Chryſte, is any other thing than the hearte of a faithfull man, and he that ſercheth it without, ſhal both loſe his paines and remayne fruſtrate of his hope.</p>
            <p n="25">25 Let vs ſpeake (my brethren) of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chryſte and his communication, as people prouing and féeling in our ſelues what it is to be nouriſhed in oure conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and ſoules, with the preſence &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, otherwiſe to what vſe will ſerue vs our ſubtill interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular declarations whiche wée bryng foorth? In the ende, the worlde is not ſo blynde, but they can and will vnderſtand and fynde, that we are rather ledde by a ſpirit of ſtomack than of the true zeale of Gods glorie, in the ende euery one will ſée that thoſe preachers ſearche no other
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:9172:26"/> thing than to mainteyne them ſelues in the friendſhip of the world.</p>
            <p n="26">26 But nowe to returne to the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the vnderſtandyng that wée <note place="margin">The vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of the wordes of the holy Supper.</note> haue giuen to this place of the holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, let vs conſyder, that if in all things that Chriſte our Lorde hath propounded to manyfeſt the neceſſitie that wee haue to be in him and he in vs, wée ſhold ſerche a preſence corporall and fleſhly, it ſhould bée (as who ſay) neuer to come to ende: for in the olde Teſtament Chriſte hath bin propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to vs in diuers creatures, as a lamb, <hi rend="roman">Manna,</hi> Water, Stone, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, meate, bread, feaſts, &amp; other things, as may bée ſéene by ſuche as reade the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture. Hée him ſelfe in his prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings doth cal him a way, a doore, bread of children, a vyne, with other like thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. <note place="margin">Note the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurditie of the falſe interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the wordes of the Supper.</note> Now, if in place where Chriſt ſayd: I am the doore, who entreth not by mée ſhall not be ſaued: he had ſayd this, I am he, ſhewyng with his finger a doore, ſhal we ſay for al that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chryſt hath tranſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or tranſubſtanciate him ſelf into the matter of a doore: if our redéemer in place
<pb facs="tcp:9172:27"/> where he ſayd, I am the vine and you are the bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches, had ſayd, this am I, ſhewing <note place="margin">Note the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of theſe words.</note> the vine, and that are you, handlyng the branches, coulde we ſay for all that, that Ieſus Chryſt would comunicate his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance into a grape, and that the Apoſtles ſhould be tranſnatured into braunches? ſure who were of ſuch opinion, diſcouered ſufficiently his ignorance and infirmitie.</p>
            <p n="27">27 Notwithſtanding, (you others my brethren) make your principall piller vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſuche manner of ſpeakings, and all to make the poore ignorant people beleue that Chryſte hath made promiſe to giue himſelfe with the bread, bycauſe that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing taken bread, and breaking it, he ſaid this is my body: which woordes (ſimply vnderſtanded) are as much as to ſay, my body which is broken, offered, deliuered, and ſacrifiſed for you, is bread, or like too this bread whiche you breake, eate and digeſt for the nouriture of your body: In like ſort, I being the heuenly bread, ſhal be broken for you, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end you may haue ſpiritual &amp; eternal life: therfore do &amp; cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, this breaking and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:9172:27"/> receite of bread in remembrance of me.</p>
            <p n="28">28 To make co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion of this matter, I vnderſtand that our redéemer Ieſus is <note place="margin">Compariſon betwene the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Adam.</note> the frute of lyfe, who hauing put himſelf on the trée of the Croſſe, hath defaced the ſinne and tranſgreſſion, whiche the frute of the trée defended brought to vs: And e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as Adam, hauyng eaten of ſuche a frute, did make hymſelf enimie of God: in contrary manner, when wée partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate with Ieſus Chriſt crucified, we are receiued into the good fauour and loue of oure Heauenly Father, and that by the onely bountie, merite, and interceſſion of the ſelf hée, who on the trée of the croſſe did conſtitute hymſelfe the frute of lyfe for vs, beyng aſſured that the participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that precious Frute is not done either by water, wine, bread, or any other creature whatſoeuer, but by the woorke and operation indicible of the holy ſpirit, who hauing called the choſen and prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate of God, doeth teache them their <note place="margin">Meane to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Chryſt. Election. Vocation. Penance.</note> ſinnes and abhominable tranſgreſſions by meane of the preſentation of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Lawe, hée ſheweth vnto them theyr
<pb facs="tcp:9172:28"/> damnation &amp; ſentence of eternall death, the whiche they féele ſo in their heartes, that by experience they may well aſſure them ſelues, that the ire and wrathe of God hath bin ſo manifeſted to them, that they haue ſwallowed pangs of death, and <note place="margin">The true pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration to knowe Chryſt is to know the neceſsitie wee haue of hym.</note> ſéene before their eyes the throate of hell confounde and deuoure them: there they fynd the frute of the trée of knowledge of good and euill: they ſorrowe and wéepe with a penaunce moſt bitter the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bankets or repaſts whiche they haue taken of ſuch a meate and fruite, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the perſon of their father Adam, but alſo with their proper mouth.</p>
            <p n="29">29 After that by ſuch means, the holy ſpirit hath abaſed the arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of man, his pride and preſumption, and ſhewed him by experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the diffinitiue ſentence &amp; areſt irreuocable of the eternal ageinſt ſinners, he beginneth to comfort and giue him good hope, ſhewing him (as a far off) <note place="margin">The faithefull feele the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt in their hart.</note> the Trée of lyfe, and the viuifying fruite hanging vpon it, the whiche by little and little, degrée and degrée, fayth and fayth, and vertue and vertue, makes him eate,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:9172:28"/> ſwallow and digeſt the heauenly bread Ieſus Chryſt, yea with ſuch experience &amp; féeling, that no meat in the world of how great nouriture ſoeuer it be, is ſo ſenſible in the bodie, as the frute of life (Ieſus Chryſt) is in the ſoules of the faythfull, with ſuch manifeſtation by good woorkes outwardly, that others may ſee &amp; knowe with what meate they be fed.</p>
            <p n="30">30 For when we eate of euery other <note place="margin">The life of a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth that he hath Chriſt in him.</note> meate, the body of him that eateth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth only the preſence of the meate. But in ſuche as eate Chryſt, the true frute of the trée of life, is diſcerned ſuche an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in their perſons, ſuch ioy and pacience in afflictions, ſuch care to mortifie the old Adam, ſuch a renu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciation of the things of the world, with affection to the lyfe eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, that their neighbours and freendes acompanying them, may ſée that they eat other meate than the deuourers of cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies do.</p>
            <p n="31">31 When they haue truely, eſſential<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and really participated of the bodie and bloud of Chryſte (by faith as is ſayd) of Ieſus Chryſte, all entier, true God,
<pb facs="tcp:9172:29"/> and true man, they aſſure them ſelues of ſuche a coniunction with him, that they haue no néede to goe to ſearche hym, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> armorie of Préeſts, or betwene the hands of men, too receiue him either with the bread or with the water, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fully aſſured that Ieſus Chriſt dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in them, and that they be fleſh of his fleſh, and bones of his bones.</p>
            <p n="32">32 And yet for all this, they forbeare not to aproch to the holy table of the Lord to celebrate the holy Supper with theyr brethren and chyldren of the ſame hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father: Neither go they thither to receiue Chryſte of newe in bread or in wyne, by grace or merite: but their firſt cauſe of going thither is, to certifie to al the church that they are of the number of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> receiue Ieſus Chriſt for their on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly redéemer &amp; ſauior, for their eternal ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificator, their chief king, lord, ſouerain prophet &amp; doctor to teach them in al truth.</p>
            <p n="33">33 Secondly, they take the holy ſupper as a gage &amp; aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the good wil of the heuenly father towards the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo conſtant &amp; firme, that it wil neuer
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:9172:29"/> change. For euen as God hath promiſed by othe, that the ſacrificator ſhal be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, euen ſo ſhall be the ſacrificature and ſacrifice for expiation of our ſinnes.</p>
            <p n="34">34 Thirdly, they receiue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Supper the ſeale of ratification &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmation of grace, with reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciliation prononou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced by the preaching of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell, to the end y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by ſuch mean, faith might be augmented in them, ſeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God is not only co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented to giue them y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> word of reconciliation, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign his promiſes with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſonne, but hath alſo ſigned and ſealed his Goſpell of reconciliation with ſeales declaring in a wonderfull maner, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very things conteined in the letters patentes and promis of the goſpel &amp; happy newes.</p>
            <p n="35">35 Fourthly, the faithful ſee in the holy Supper, as in a table and liuely portrait, the communion and participation which they haue inwardly in their hartes with Ieſus Chriſt, knowing alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al the nori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture &amp; ſpiritual vigor which they ſee in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> comes of the preſence of hym whom they conſider and beholde figured &amp; repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the holy and ſacred Ceremonie of
<pb facs="tcp:9172:30"/> the Supper: by meane of which conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, they render thanks to the Lorde <note place="margin">Sacrifice of thanks giuing in the holy Supper.</note> for the fayth, hope, mortification, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie whiche they féele to be communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to them by the power and benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of him that dwelleth in them. And by this mean, their faith being augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, they participate more &amp; more with Ieſus Chriſt once receiued.</p>
            <p n="36">36 Finally they lerne in the holy ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, the vnitie and charitie whiche wée <note place="margin">Confirmation and augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt receiued in the Supper.</note> ought to haue one with an other: And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wée proteſt in the receite of the holie Sacrament to be one bodie &amp; one church, membres of one ſoueraine heade Ieſus Chriſt, it is good reſon alſo that we lerne to imitate the <hi rend="roman">Sympathia</hi> and mutuall compaſſion whiche wée ſée dayly in oure humaine bodies, whereof if one of oure armes bée hurte, the other ſerueth and comforteth it, the féet refuſing theyr pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per office to march and go, are content to <note place="margin">The holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per repreſentes vnto vs a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly charitie of one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> kéepe themſelues in bed, to the ende the arme being hurt may bée in reſt, the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke is ſatiſfied with a ſlender repaſte, to the end to eaſe that part that is diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:9172:30"/> in effect, euery one of the outward &amp; inward membres, do ſo acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modate their office and function to the eaſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the hurte place, that in them may be noted a wonderful harmonie &amp; league of one part with an other, the ſame alſo being lyuely repreſented and expreſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vnto vs in the celebration of the holy Supper of the Lorde, to the ende that euery one of vs, may with moſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent care, laboure to preſerue the vnitie of the body of Chriſt, and ſupporting one an other, may learne to couer the faults of our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, pardon their wrongs, not to rebuke and exaggerate too muche their ignorances, but rather to interpret them to the beſt, and to teache them with cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. Let vs learne in the celebration of the holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to make vs partakers of the afflictions and perſecutions of our brethren, whome we confeſſe in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of the ſupper too bée the members of Chryſt with vs.</p>
            <p n="37">37 Behold here (in effect my dere bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) one parte of the ſpirituall frutes that the children of God receiue in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite
<pb facs="tcp:9172:31"/> of the Supper of oure Lorde truly admynyſtred and ſimply vnderſtanded, knowing right well that Chriſte had no other meaning in the inſtitution of thoſe ſacraments, than to manyfeſt by viſible wordes (as Saint Auguſtine ſayeth) the good wil of God towards men, that is, to purge, waſhe, and make them cleane by the water of his grace, and by the bloud of his propre ſon, to conioyn, knit, &amp; incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate them with him, euen as the meat is made one thing with our fleſh, in ſuch ſort that eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as in the exterior preaching of the goſpel the Lord doth offer and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to all the world the benefit of recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation by Chriſt, in like maner the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments be as a table or ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhop, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the benignitie, mercy &amp; charitie of our God, be expoſed to euery one, offered and repreſented liuely in the tables: And mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſhal they be, who not ſerching the lyfe &amp; liuely refection and true waſhing within, do embrace the corruptible and deceiuable elements, and double miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhal they be, who naming themſelues Doctors of the truthe, and paſtors of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:9172:31"/> troupe of God, would féede the ſoules of their ſhéepe with meates that wil periſh and corrupt.</p>
            <p n="38">38 But now to return to our purpoſe begon, I tooke occaſion (my dere beloued <note place="margin">The occaſion of the writing of this ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> brethren) to write you theſe few lines, as ſéeing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſmal frute of my requeſt on your behalf, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſpake to <hi rend="roman">Monſieur Mathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Yllyricus,</hi> who, was ſayd to be the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendent of your churche, with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I perſuaded very modeſtly to ſhew vnto you, and conſider himſelfe the infancie of this church, perſecuted &amp; thretned on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide, aſſayled with many enimies, and battred with diuerſitie of opinions, with aduiſe beſides, that the tyme was more proper to preache and teach to the people the faythe and hope whiche wée ought to vſe to mortifie oure wicked affections, with a regarde of care to enterteine the league of charitie one with an other, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to impart with the ſimple and ignorant ſort ſuche debates and queſtions, as wée haue rayſed vppon the matter of oure confeſſions: Séeyng withal, that ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are rather pronounced of a iolitie
<pb facs="tcp:9172:32"/> of the hart to preferre our eloquence, and procure to our ſelues a peculiar eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on amongeſt men, than of purpoſe neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the edificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our pietie: which albeit he ſéemed to like of, with a diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to admit and performe my requeſts, yet contrarily, I ſee he is eyther the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor or inſtigatour of a confeſſion of faith which you haue ſet a broach in this chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of <hi rend="italic">Antwerpe:</hi> in which confeſſion, I can not only fynd any one point of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> three mentioned in my conference with him, but alſo it ſéemes to certen, that you haue raiſed this confeſſion expreſly to trouble this poore afflicted churche. The Lorde of his goodneſſe giue you true knowledge and repentance of that whiche you do: for touching the chiefe point of oure Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that is to ſay, Faith, I fynde not in your confeſſion many texts nor places which kindle the heart of man to imbrace the doctrine of Ieſus Chriſte. A thyng whiche I coulde eaſily appointe with my fynger, if I woulde as vainely employ my time in confutation, as I ſée a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber do at this day in diſputation: onely I
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:9172:32"/> thanke GOD, that by other meanes hée hath taught me the doctrine of his truth: for if at my firſte arriuall, I had encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred your confeſſion of faith, to lerne me to be a chriſtian, I coulde not haue much profited in a leſſon of fayth ſo full of que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, debates, and diſſentions.</p>
            <p n="39">39 Deare brethren, if you will with iudgement reade ouer that, whiche your author hath written in youre name, you ſhall fynde, that neither <hi rend="roman">Scotus</hi> nor any other Sophiſters of the Papiſts, haue ſo muche endarkned the doctrine of Ieſus Chryſt, nor clad it with ſo many queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as certeine of you haue done: wherof (for example) let vs ſuruey briefly foure certeine points, and that more to reueale the ſlender edification that their readers may hope for of ſuche leſſons, than to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comber our ſelues with the confutation of ſuch vanities. <note place="margin">Reade the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the confeſsion of faythe of Yl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyric, the better to vnderſtande the articles fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="40">40 Touching that whiche you ſay of our inheritaunce of the originall ſynne, and frée will loſt, the world it ſelfe dooth declare well inough at this day, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one hath gotten a good lump of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance
<pb facs="tcp:9172:33"/> of the corruption of Adam, and the originall ſinne as they call it, neither doe your wrytings diſpence or diſcharge you of your parte thereof. And I beléeue (as you ſay) that men now a dayes haue not any Frée wyll, ſéeyng it maye bée further beléeued, that there bée a greate manye that haue ſlender ſenſe and well woorſe vnderſtanding, as béeing altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ruled and caried ouer by their affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p n="41">41 Touching the matter of the incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the ſonne of GOD, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of man, I could wel haue par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned you the obmyſſyon of the ſubtill queſtions you vſe therin, ſearching curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly the houſe wherin Chryſt dwelleth. Item, what make we of aſcenſion? or the ſignification of this woord heauen? or the right hande of God? ſo that you woulde teach vs the true meane to receiue Ieſus Chryſte into oure ſelues, ſéeing it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him, in reſpect of his goodneſſe, too make his dwellyng in the hearts of the faithful and regenerate. Otherways of what vſe is Ieſus Chryſt to vs being ſo
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:9172:33"/> farre from the hart of man as you make hym? B. 4.</p>
            <p n="42">42 Touching youre place of iuſtifying faith, I vnderſtande not your language, where you ſay that only fayth, by meane whereof wée take (as of a hande) the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of Ieſus Chryſte too obteine iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, regeneration and health: and immediatly after you ſaye, that by the Sacramentes, are imputed and applied too vs the Iuſtyce and merite of Ieſus Chryſte. B. 4.</p>
            <p n="43">43 In the doctrine of iuſtification you ſay it is a moſte harde queſtion to knowe what is that true iuſtice whiche makes vs iuſte and agréeable to God, with at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teinement of eternall lyfe: but I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that without ſo many argumentes, confutations, and ſubtilties, you hadde ſhewed to the poore and ignorant people, what is the chriſtian iuſtice, and by what meane ſhe is giuen to vs. B. 5.</p>
            <p n="44">44 Touching the point of good works you ſay that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> works which me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to cal good, are thoſe which God demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds in his word, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe which be regenerat
<pb facs="tcp:9172:34"/> and guided by the ſpirit of God, are they which ſhew the frutes of a good Trée: I beléeue it well, and conclude vpon youre ſaying, that who hath not zeale, loue, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, who ſuffereth not all thyngs with pacience, taketh euery thing in the beſte parte, couereth the faultes of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and laboureth not to put peace in place of diſſentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, can not haue regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And touchyng the reſt of your que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, whether good woorks concurre in iuſtification, as a cauſe formall or effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, the ſimple people hath not to do, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting themſelues with this beléef, that regeneration &amp; faith without good works is a mere hipocriſie and thing dead, and that it is neceſſary, that our newe obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience ſerue as witneſſe of oure reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation and iuſtification.</p>
            <p n="45">45 Nowe (deare brethren) as I am voyde of intent herein eyther to examin or exaggerate the newneſſe of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and much leſſe to confute it by ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentes, ſo I will leaue to the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Reader, your excuſe in cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of the liuing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:9172:34"/> God vnder pretext of certeine gloſes and diſtinctions vnworthy to be vttered: for here we do not diſpute whether the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement not too make any images of veneration, be a commandement par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, or an appendix of an other, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be ceremoniall or morall: but we will here maynteine that it is an audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie moſt curſed to cut off from the law of oure God any one woord, ſéeing ſpecially that that ſumme and content of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement is ſo ſhort and compendious, that it conteineth but ten commaundements, the which if God woulde haue abridged, he knew better how to do it than we, and therfore ſuch as vndertake to correct his ſtile and accuſe him of prolixitie, giue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient proofe of their abhominable teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
            <p n="46">46 But let vs now come to the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall poynt of your debate and auncient queſtion, the which vpon a brauery you ſéeme to renue vppon euery purpoſe and place, without hauing reſpect to the gret ſlaunder of thoſe that bée weake. Firſt you vtter the ſumme of your confeſſion of
<pb facs="tcp:9172:35"/> the Supper in theſe words: <note place="margin">The opinion of Mathias Yl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyricus and his companions touching the Supper.</note> 
               <hi rend="italic">Credimus igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Christo affirmanti, quòd corpus &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis eius verè ac realiter in ſacra Coena ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, detur<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> externo modo accipiendum cum pane &amp; vino, non fide tantùm, aut ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter, id<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tam ab indignis, quám à dignis ſumatur, &amp; contraria docentes, cum Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtana confeſſione conſentiendo, damnamus.</hi> That is to ſay: Wée beléeue in Chryſte who aſſureth vs that his body and bloud be truly and really in the ſacred ſupper, and that it is giuen vs in taking it out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly with the bread and wyne, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with faith and ſpiritually: the which body is eaten as wel of the vnworthy, as of thoſe that be woorthy: And thoſe that ſhall teache the contrary, wée (ſtickyng to the Confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auspurge)</hi> do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them.</p>
            <p n="47">47 Sée here (my brethren) your goodly entrie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> article of your Supper, which we may, not improperly, liken to that of the newe inquiſitors, who condemne, anathematize, excommunicate, and call Heretikes, and confounders of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, all thoſe whiche receiue not their confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:9172:35"/> which me thinke you do alſo as of purpoſe to maynteyne youres of <hi rend="italic">Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpurge,</hi> as though it were a fyfth Goſpel or newe Symbole of the Crede. What ſhall wée ſaye (brethren) too theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? haue you no ſhame that men of good iudgement and vnderſtandyng, ſhoulde reade ſuche haultie and raſhe woordes? Who are they that haue ſet the authour of the Confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auſpurge,</hi> or that of yours in ſuche authoritie or degrée of the Churche, tht they may pronounce Sentence of damnation ageynſte ſuche as wyll not admit theyr interpretation vppon a place or Text of the Scripture? What is hée of any iudgement at all, who wyll not feare to forſake the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the Papiſtes, to enter into an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, almoſt of lyke condition? Wée call the Pope Antechryſt, tyraunt and but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of mens conſciences, bycauſe that without libertie to heare men ſpeake, he condemneth and excommunicates them, and yet your doings are nothing inferior to his crueltie, in pronouncing condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, not onely ageinſt your enimies,
<pb facs="tcp:9172:36"/> but alſo ageinſt ſuche as you receiue for youre brethren and companions in the woorke of the Lorde, and who no leſſe for the duetie of Chriſtians, than to take away the ſlaunder from the Churche of Chryſte, do ſearche by all theyr poſſible meanes too lyue in loue and friendſhip with you.</p>
            <p n="48">48 I could willingly ſay to the author of your confeſſion, as the Apoſtle ſayth: my brother, my frend, what art thou that <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Rom.</hi> 14.</note> condemnes the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of an other? Who hath giuen thée ſuch power? Art thou his redemer? Art thou his iudge? Art thou he in the name of whome he hath bin bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? Hath he not a maiſter, who, if he fall wil raiſe him agein, and hath the power to do it? But of what purpoſe are theſe words, when we finde our harts ſo hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that wée féele not at al the very cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſements, which God lets fal vpon our heades.</p>
            <p n="49">49 Let vs marke and conſider what miſerable iſſues our prechings, confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wrytings, and commentaries, bring forth: Let vs alſo behold what frutes are
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:9172:36"/> brought to oure audience by oure words, what reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of life in our churches, wherin raign ſtill wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neſſe, lubricities, gluttonies, dronkenneſſe, vſurie, deceits, with a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſuch like vices, which we let paſſe, making our ſelues many tymes (by winking) companions to thoſe that commit them, ſwallowing (as oure Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chryſt ſayth) the Camels, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter paſſing by the cloutes the litle gnats, which meaneth that we pronounce con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation ageinſt ſuch who pierce not the ſubtilties of oure interpretations in Chryſtes Supper: making ſmall recke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the crimes and diſſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which are committed dayly afore oure eyes I pray you what may meane ſo many ſorts of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munications of Chriſt, the one phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall, <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Yllyricus in the text of his admonition maketh.</hi> 4. ſorts of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications of Chryſt.</note> and an other myſtical, an other ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, and an other ſacramentall, togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo with thoſe whyche you put in your confeſſion, the one common both to the good &amp; to the euil, when they ſay, this is my body, and the other, when they ſay, Do this in remembraunce of me. Thoſe with ſuch like co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munications of Chriſte,
<pb facs="tcp:9172:37"/> wée neuer learned in the woorde of God, but of the contrary, wée knowe for truth that there is but one mean to receiue Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chryſte, and haue communication with him, that is to ſay, liuely faith, and that accompanied with repentaunce and <note place="margin">Meane to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Chryſt by only faith.</note> penance of our ſinnes paſſed, &amp; newneſſe of life to come. I would to God we were wel taught and exerciſed in this manner of communicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chryſt: for touching the reſt, what aſſuraunce may wée take of the doctrine of youre article, whiche is not drayned out of the word of God, but rather of the interpretations of men? I praye you ſhewe mée where it is that Chryſte affirmeth, that his bodye and bloud be truely and really in the bread, vnder the bread, or within the breade of the Supper, and that he giueth hymſelfe to bée eaten exteriorly with the breade and wine, the ſame being not doone not onely by Fayth, or ſpiritually, but that he is eaten as well of the vnworthy as thoſe that be worthy.</p>
            <p n="50">50 Me thinks (deare brethren) that, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you wil be eſtéemed ſo diligent in the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:9172:37"/> obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the words of the ſcripture, as preferring nothing which is not dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen out of the ſame, it is neceſſary you know, that in al your article there is not one word of the words of Chriſt: but we <note place="margin">What co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betwene Chriſt and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall.</note> knowe that both he himſelfe and his apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle teacheth vs the contrary, ſaying, that the vnbeléeuing and vnwoorthy can not <note place="margin">2. <hi rend="roman">Cor.</hi> 6.</note> poſſeſſe Chriſte, nor be membres of him, ſeing they haue not a mouth of fayth to receiue him.</p>
            <p n="51">51 Beſides, I ſée that your very confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion doth not accorde at all, with that of <hi rend="italic">Auspurge,</hi> wherof you make ſo greate a buckler, no leſſe to maynteyne you in the good opynion of the worlde, than to bryng your ſelues in, vnder the protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of princes and potentates, who at the beginning, vſed very wiſely and chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianlye the preſentation of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. For the woordes of the Authour bée theſe, Article. 10. <hi rend="italic">De Coena Domina do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, quòd cum pane &amp; vino verè exhibean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur corpus et ſanguis Christi, veſcentibus in coena domini,</hi> that is to ſay: Touching the Supper of the Lorde, they teache, that
<pb facs="tcp:9172:38"/> with the bread and wine be exhibited the body and bloud of Chryſte, to thoſe that eate the Supper of the Lorde.</p>
            <p n="52">52 In theſe woordes the Confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auſpurge</hi> make no mention to receyue the body of Chriſte really and exteriorly, as you ſay in youres, neither make they mention at all that the worthie and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie do receiue it.</p>
            <p n="53">53 But herevnto you ſay, that we haue not the true and incorrupte confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auspurge,</hi> but that you haue certein Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies and exemplaries thereof beſt correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whiche you follow in your doctrine: is it poſſible (brethren) you ſhoulde be ſo negligent in the correction of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion wherof you make ſo great value? I am not of opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the princes Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts wold ſuffer to be printed in their townes, articles of their confeſſion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taminated and imperfect: truly you trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble greatly the world: for if thoſe which folow not your confeſſion, be condemned by your ſentence, and you onely haue the true copie of this confeſſion, wée muſte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neceſſarily come to you as to a ſpring
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:9172:38"/> or fountain of truth and helth: ſome may ſay (as in deriſion of thoſe things,) that wée muſt come on pilgrimage to ſearche your regiſters and bookeſhops, as in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes paſt they went to <hi rend="italic">Ieruſale, Rome,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">S. Iames,</hi> Oh good God, what mockerie, what preſumption of people? But, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent you of cauſe of complainte ageynſt vs, and that your inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration be more manyfeſtly diſcouered, we will recite the article of your incorrupt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion, which as you ſay to be reſerued with you, ſo you ſhall fynde it beareth not a worde of that which you haue vttered.</p>
            <p n="54">54 Youre wordes be theſe: <hi rend="italic">Sequimur igitur in hac controuerſia ſententiam decimi articuli Augustanae confeſſionis: porrò ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">See the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. H.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi rend="italic">ille decimus ita habet in incorrupta confeſſione, quam ſequimur: De coena Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini docent, quod corpus &amp; ſanguis Christi verè adſint, &amp; distribuantur veſcentibus in Coena domini: &amp; improbant ſecus docentes.</hi> That is to ſay: Wée followe in this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion and debate, the aduiſe and ſentence of the tenth Article of the Confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auſpurge,</hi> which tenth article is writen
<pb facs="tcp:9172:39"/> in this ſorte, in the confeſſion whiche we followe, whiche is not corrupted: It is taught, touching the ſupper of the Lorde, that the body and bloud of Chryſt be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſent, and bée diſtributed to ſuche as eate in the Supper of the Lorde, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are they approued whiche teache o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wayes.</p>
            <p n="55">55 Nowe (brethren) I pray you ſhew mée where it is that you finde here your realities, and vbiquities, or that the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy do eate the body of Chryſt, with other ſorts of doctrines whiche you haue preferred, and wold authoriſe them with the confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auspurge,</hi> whyche not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, wée wyll not receiue as a rule of our Chriſtianitie, and muche leſſe the Confeſſion of any other man that is vppon earth.</p>
            <p n="56">56 We wil be chriſtians, and ſo be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, we wil follow the confeſſion of faith, whiche oure GOD the father, and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chryſte his Sonne haue lefte vntoo vs: that is too ſaye, the dyuyne woorde in the olde and new Teſtament, as the ſumme of oure Religion: Wée receiue
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:9172:39"/> the ſimbols of fayth receiued of olde time in the Churche: we haue not bin bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in the names of <hi rend="roman">Martine, Zwingli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> or <hi rend="roman">Caluyn,</hi> but in the name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Sonne and the holy Ghoſte: by whiche meanes, wée deteſte and abhorre all thoſe names and ſurnames of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialities, that is to ſaye, Martiniſtes, Zwinglians, and Caluiniſts, with other like, knowing very well that GOD is greately diſpleaſed with ſuche ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and partialities in the doctrine of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: And I wiſh with al my hart, that the doctours whiche haue taught here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and ſuche as at this day doe preache the Goſpell, were of more modeſtie and wiſdom, and purely conſecrated to ſearch the glorie of the Lorde, and not theyr owne proper prayſe: then ſhould the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple bée in more lybertie of conſcience, and the worſhippers of one onely God, and not of mortall men, ignoraunt and blynde, who, makyng them ſelues as Idolls, doe deſire to bée followed and holden in greate admyration: I would in God that euery one would ſay with
<pb facs="tcp:9172:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:9172:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9172:41"/> Sainct Iohn the Baptiſt, it is méete that Ieſus Chriſte be exalted and magnified, and that I be diminiſhed and vnknown: it is to Ieſus Chryſt, to whom we ought to ſend the poore ſoules, deſirous to fynde knowledge and iuſtice, and not to youre confeſſions, inſtitutions, catechiſmes, or commentaries.</p>
            <p n="57">57 For the reſte (brethren) you ſéeme to complaine of the greate diuerſitie of interpretation that many haue pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vpon the words of the Supper, which partely I can not denie, bycauſe many deſirous to make their church apart, doe raiſe a value or eſtimation of them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues among their audience, with pretence to celebrate theyr owne names: from whence it procéeds, that hauing but one truth, and one ſimple intelligence in the words of Chryſt, all ſuch as digreſſe from the ſame, to vſe ſome ſtrange and new or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, do euery one bring into the churche his innouation.</p>
            <p n="58">58 But I beſech you conſider, whether amongſt thoſe that receiue the tenth arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auſpurge,</hi> there be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:9172:41"/> any diuerſitie of interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to the end that if you will haue all the worlde (for the eſchuing of the condemnation of your ſentence) to followe your confeſſion, you firſt labour to eſtabliſh an accord amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt your ſelues, and then euery one will deliberate vppon that he hath to doe. For you being deuided amongſt youre ſelues, and of diuers opinions, we are ignorant in the part we ought to follow to eſcape your condemnation.
<note place="parend">They of the Confeſsion of Auſpurge agree not amongſt themſelues vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the words of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Reade the boke named Antitheſe, of the true and falſe expoſition of the tenth Article of the Confeſsion of Auſpurge, the Author of the ſame is Sybran Andreas.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="59">59 Firſt you know well that <hi rend="roman">Mathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Yllyricus,</hi> whom I thinke to be the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of your confeſſion, is not of opinion with thoſe that haue compoſed and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auſpurge,</hi> and you and he are not ignorant of the contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, debates and diſcentions, which be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen till this day betwéene him &amp; others: All which I will not here repete, bicauſe
<pb facs="tcp:9172:42"/> my intente is not, to kindle the coales of diſſention, but rather to quenche them, I will not bryng to lyght the faultes of others, but rather couer and hyde them, albéeit it is eaſye for euery man to ſée, bothe howe thyngs haue paſſed, and how they are nowe vſed, and that by Bookes that are printed.
<note place="parend">Touchyng the diſſention of M. Yllyricus with Ph. Melancthon, and thoſe of the Confeſsion of Auſpurge, reade the Epiſtles of Melancthon in many places, but chiefly the page. 452. Alſo the Actes Synodals imprinted in the yeare. 1559. Alſo the anſweres giuen to the Legate of Saxon by Ph. Melancthon.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="60">60 Touching the breaking &amp; bruſing of breade, you ſée I am ſure, that in thys towne of <hi rend="italic">Antwerpe,</hi> the Miniſters be not of accorde. I leaue aparte the truthe of the Queſtion, which you call indifferent, notwithſtandyng that the inſtitution of the Lorde beareth by manyfeſt wordes, the breaking of the bread. S. Paule cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Supper the breking of bread, which alſo all the auncient church do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue: And for my part, I am of opinion
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:9172:42"/> that in the ceremonie of the holie Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, the breaking of breade oughte to bée obſerued, as ſignifying and aſſuring to vs that Ieſus Chryſte was offered bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for vs: for the reſt, as when Chriſt celebrated the ſupper, whether the bread he had then betwene his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, was great <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Seeke the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. K. 10. &amp;. 11.</hi>
               </note> or little, I leaue the deciſion of that que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion to <hi rend="roman">Monſieur Mathias Yllyricus,</hi> who ſayth that Ieſus Chriſte in the Supper, brake the bread, bycauſe the cakes were too great, and hée had not made prouiſion of litle waffernes as we vſe, ſo that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie forced him to breake the breade without hauing intent to teach vs any thing by the breaking of the bread.</p>
            <p n="61">61 The Churches of the moſte noble prince elector and Countie Palatyne, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auſpurge,</hi> and yet in youre Catechiſme you teache that the vnfaithful and vnworthy do not eate the body of Chryſte in the Sacrament, the which is ageinſt youre article, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ageinſt the confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auſpurge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="62">62 The diuins of the renoumed prince of <hi rend="roman">Heſſe</hi> haue receiued the confeſſion of
<pb facs="tcp:9172:43"/> 
               <hi rend="italic">Auspurge,</hi> and yet <hi rend="roman">Andreas Hyperius</hi> doctour of the vniuerſitie of <hi rend="italic">Marpurge,</hi> belongyng to the ſayde Prince, receyued the Confeſſion preſented by the Straun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers out of the towne of <hi rend="italic">Weaſell,</hi> againſt which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion <hi rend="roman">Heſhuſsius</hi> his compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and yours, haue raiſed many deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, to baniſh from the countrey ſuch as folowed the ſayd confeſſion, the ſame ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing manifeſtly, that you and your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions be not of accorde with the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the ſayd prince.</p>
            <p n="63">63 <hi rend="roman">Iohannes Pincerus,</hi> a man lerned &amp; no leſſe deuoute as you knowe, albeit he receiued the confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auspurge,</hi> writ notwithſtanding, a boke againſt the ſayd <hi rend="roman">Heſhuſsius,</hi> refuting the opinions of the Supper, and other thyngs, the whiche <hi rend="roman">Heſhuſsius</hi> nameth him ſelfe to be of the confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auspurge,</hi> and youre adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and confederate to maynteyne this diſſention.</p>
            <p n="64">64 In the yeare 1565. The right noble prince elect of <hi rend="italic">Saxon,</hi> preſented to the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of <hi rend="italic">Wittemberge,</hi> the writings of <hi rend="roman">Brentius</hi> &amp; <hi rend="roman">Iames Andreas,</hi> as vpon mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:9172:43"/> to examin them touching their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Supper, wherevnto the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie anſwered, that the ſayd <hi rend="roman">Brentius</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Andreas,</hi> vſed in this matter diuers and ſundry orders of ſpeche, bothe newe, daungerous, and altogither vnknowne to the auncient Churche, that is to ſay, that the humanitie of Chriſt was diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into euery place: that the humaniti-of Chriſte was Creatour of all things, that <hi rend="roman">Iames Andreas</hi> confounded the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of languages or propreties in the perſon of Chriſt, and that they fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that the vniuerſitie of <hi rend="italic">Tubinga</hi> and the church of <hi rend="italic">Wittenburgh</hi> were troubled with theſe innouations of doctrin, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to ceaſſe from ſuche diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with contentment onely to beléeue that the words of Chryſte be true, when he ſayeth, this is my body. Nowe my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, what part I pray you, ſhould wee followe, ſeing both the one and the other be of the confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auspurge?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="65">65 <hi rend="roman">Paule Eberus</hi> denyeth expreſly, that the vnworthy eate the fleſhe of Chriſte, who being of the confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auſpurge,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9172:44"/> doth neither agrée with you, nor yet with <hi rend="roman">Brentius,</hi> who mainteyneth, that Iudas (in the Supper) did as well receiue the body of Chryſt, as S. Iohn, or S. Peter.</p>
            <p n="66">66 The eight article of the confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auspurge,</hi> doth teach, that the vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full are not members of the churche, and therefore receiue not but the outeward ſignes of the Supper. So that when you ſay that the vnworthie receyue the body of Chriſt, you are there contrary to your owne proper confeſſion. I pray you what coniunction is there betwene lighte and darkneſſe? What aquaintance betwene Ieſus Chryſte and <hi rend="roman">Belyal?</hi> No, let vs ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remembre and reteyne that which the Prophet ſayeth, that God loueth not the wicked nor their wickedneſſe, neither ſhall the vngodly dwell with him.</p>
            <p n="67">67 <hi rend="roman">Phillip Melancthon,</hi> author of the confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auspurge,</hi> in the apologie of the ſame confeſſion doth teach, that the participation of the body of Chryſt is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of the faithfull by the meditation of his benefits: then to receiue Chryſt, it is not nedefull too gnawe hym or breake
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:9172:44"/> him with our téeth. Beſides, the wicked which haue no meditation, nor godly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordation of the benefites of Chryſte, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they chaw the bread, yet can they not receiue Chryſte by the ſaying of the ſame Author, to whome your doctrine is contrarie in this poynt.</p>
            <p n="68">68 <hi rend="roman">Martine Luther</hi> hath bin eſtemed a good interpreter &amp; vnderſtander of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auſpurge,</hi> and yet he ſaith that the very iuyce and mary of the holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, is to receiue an aſſuraunce of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of oure ſinnes by the ſacrifice of Chryſt. Thoſe then that ſay that the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull and vnworthy receiue the bodye of Chryſt, which is the iuyce and marow of the ſacrament, be contrary to the ſaid doctor: and by conſequent, to the confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi rend="italic">Auspurge,</hi> the which you do in your Article.</p>
            <p n="69">69 The Duke of <hi rend="italic">Wittenburgh,</hi> wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth and meaneth that his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion agrée with that of <hi rend="italic">Auspurge,</hi> and yet the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Supper in his confeſſion is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted by the words of <hi rend="roman">Ezechiell,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, this Quarey or tyle is the towne of <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Ezech.</hi> 4.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:9172:45"/> 
               <hi rend="italic">Ieruſalem</hi> &amp;c. That is to ſay, doth ſignifie or meane the town of <hi rend="italic">Ieruſalem</hi> &amp;c. Who then will not receiue this place in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of the Supper, diſagréeth with the confeſſion of the ſaid prince, and by conſequent, with that of <hi rend="italic">Auspurge,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom is <hi rend="italic">Kemnitius,</hi> who reiects wholly this place in the matter of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</p>
            <p n="70">70 Touching this woord (vnworthy) and who ought to be called ſo, you be not of accorde: for <hi rend="roman">Heſhuſsius</hi> your compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with large arguments goeth aboute to proue that the faithful ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not any way be called vnworthy. <hi rend="italic">Kemnitius</hi> (in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary) mainteineth that the place of S. Paule treating of the vnworthyneſſe of ſuche as receiue the Supper, ought to be vnderſtanded and interpreted by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place of the Goſpell, where the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith, that he is not worthy that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chryſt enter intoo his houſe, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient doctors haue interpreted it. Which of theſe ſhall we beléeue, ſéeing they bée of contrary opinyon, and yet bothe the one and other folowers of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:9172:45"/> 
               <hi rend="italic">Auſpurge?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="71">71 The .xiij. Article of the confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auspurge,</hi> teacheth that the lauful vſe of the Sacrament demaundeth neceſſaryly Fayth, without whiche vſe, the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is no Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Thoſe then which haue not faythe in the adminiſtration of your Supper, haue not alſo, neither ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament nor body of Chriſt, and therfore the Communion that the vnworthy doe make, reſiſtes your owne confeſſion.</p>
            <p n="72">72 The .xxj. article of the confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auspurge</hi> ſayth, that for the difference of ceremonies &amp; traditions of men, a man oughte not to accuſe the other churches, and much leſſe condemne them of error, nor call them aduerſaries, who are of a contrary opinion: And yet you (my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) call the other Miniſters of thys churche, aduerſaries, enimies, and people cut off from your companie, bicauſe they do not blyſſe at the aulter the bread afore they do diſtribute it, with obſeruation of other ceremonies that are of cuſtome in your Supper.</p>
            <p n="73">73 Touching this word (with) when
<pb facs="tcp:9172:46"/> you ſay the bodye of Chryſte is receiued with the breade, you are not of accorde: for certeine of your confeſſion affirm that Chriſt is encloſed within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread, others, vppon the bread, others, as the fire with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the hoat water, others, as the fire with in the burning iron, others, as the grange or houſe within the letters or wordes of contract: in effect, who woulde recite all the ſimilituds and interpretations which they of the confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auſpurge,</hi> haue made vpon the wordes of the ſupper, and all to maynteine the doctrine of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chryſt linked with the exterior elements, ſhould finde the diſcourſe long, and the matter of ſmall purpoſe. In the ende, <hi rend="roman">Iohn Alaſco,</hi> ſuperintendent of the Church of London, being in the Church of <hi rend="italic">Franckefort,</hi> and ſeing ſuch diſſentions tending rather too diſſolue the vnitie of the Churche, than to redreſſe it, is of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that, that woorde of the confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auſpurge,</hi> where Chryſte is receiued with the bread, ſignifieth, that when the faythefull eate the breade in the Supper with their corporall mouth, their ſpirite
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:9172:46"/> with the mouth of Faith receiues Ieſus Chryſte, whiche is on the ryghte hande of GOD. And ſuche interpretation of this woorde (with) was receiued of the Senate of the towne of <hi rend="italic">Franckefort,</hi> as a declaration agréeing with the confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auſpurge,</hi> whereby the poore ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers whiche are withdrawne thither, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in peace and quyet, vntill by reaſon of other quarels, this Queſtion was eft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoones renued, by whyche meane they became in effecte, the cauſe of the diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of ſo flouriſhing a Church. There bée alſo amongeſt you that ſaye, that the bodie of Chryſte is preſente in the Supper, as Ieſus crucified, was preſent to the eyes of the <hi rend="roman">Galathians,</hi> and as the daye of Chryſte was preſent too Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham: and yet are they receiued intoo the companye of thoſe whiche maynteyne the Confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auſpurge.</hi> And bycauſe <hi rend="roman">Heſhuſius,</hi> being at the vniuerſitie of <hi rend="italic">Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delbergh,</hi> made himſelf enimie to this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, &amp; troubled the church with debates and queſtions, it is ſayd, he was baniſhed from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd vniuerſitie, like as
<pb facs="tcp:9172:47"/> diuers haue already put in writing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things belongyng to this diſſention, and others which we haue mentioned.</p>
            <p n="74">74 Beholde (brethren) one chiefe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion muche hindring many men to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the true religion, and to bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues into youre aſſemblie, as ſeing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt you ſo great diuerſitie of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And for youre partes, touching the matter of the Sacramentes, you purſue them ſo eigerly, ſo ſharply, and with ſuch animoſitie and ſtomacke, that the very blynde themſelues diſcerne in you, more deſire to obteine victorie, than zeale of God to inſtruct youre ignorant brother. For when we haue a direct wil towards our neyghboure, with a liuely touche of compaſſion of his ignorance, and haue a chriſtian deſire to manyfeſt vnto him the truth, we do not procéede by iniuries, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comunications, nor condemnations, the ſame being in déede the very effectes and motions of a contentious and arrogant ſpirite, with a minde full of felonie. But of the contrary, we vſe ſwéete and ſofte woordes of induceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, with perſuaſions
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:9172:47"/> of modeſtie, as knowing aſſuredly, that man is a kynde of creature ſo fierce of ſtomacke, as hée is not to be qualified o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than by gentle admoniſhment, and ſpecially in the caſe and queſtion of his religion, which hauing hir true foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in the bottom of his hart, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to plant perſuaſions of Religion afore we haue ouercome and gained that place with gentle allurements, and then with frute, to plant there the doctrine of faith. Beſides alſo, you labor vs greatly to enter into diſputation in this churche vpon the poynt of the Supper, which we will not refuſe, ſo that it may be done in good order and with the conſent of the ſtate: we would alſo that you agrée firſt amongeſt youre ſelues, too the ende wée might knowe what part to mainteyne: Wherin albéeit I can not but feare, that your intent was rather to ſearch matter of triumph without victorie, with occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſende of youre bookes to the nexte fayre of <hi rend="italic">Frankefort,</hi> than of a zeale &amp; pure affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to pacifie this afflicted church: to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward which God graunt vs the zeale of
<pb facs="tcp:9172:48"/> his glory. And I pray you, of what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe wold it be to vs vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the diſputation to agrée with you: ſeing that by ſuch mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, we ſhold fal into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euil wil of a great parte of the princes Proteſtantes of <hi rend="italic">Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie,</hi> who abhorre already the opinions you haue vttered of the perſon of Chryſte too bée in the preſence of the Supper? by the ſame mean alſo, we ſhould make our ſelues companions and adherents to <hi rend="roman">Yl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyricus,</hi> youre Superintendent or author of youre confeſſion, who is hated of the moſte noble Churches and Vniuerſities of <hi rend="italic">Germanie,</hi> and chiefly in <hi rend="italic">Wittenburgh,</hi> who hath bin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mother nourſe of the firſt Proteſtants. Theſe things conſidered, I ſée neither order to diſpute, nor reaſon to come to accord with him &amp; his adhere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</p>
            <p n="75">75 The ſeconde poynt, wherein I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted <hi rend="roman">Mathias Yllyricus</hi> and you too take ſome paynes, was, in the doctryne of mortyfication, a thing moſte neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for this lamentable tyme, wherein wée ſée ſo manye Epycures, ſo manye Libertines, ſo many Atheyſtes and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple abandoned to all fylthyneſſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution:
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:9172:48"/> of which ſo principall a matter you touch not one word in all youre con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, but rather with youre vnbridled order of proceding, ſhewe to the people greate example of immortification. By the whiche, thoſe that haue iudgemente in ſpirituall things, may ſee that youre doctrine and Scripture is not a doctrine taught by the Spirite of GOD, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued in his ſchoole: but rather certeine textes and propoſitions gathered oute of the papers and Bookes of others, who (peraduenture) haue proued better than wée, that whiche they haue taughte and left in writing.</p>
            <p n="76">76 The laſt part of my requeſt to <hi rend="roman">M. Yllyricus</hi> was, to exhort you to enterteyn a charitable and louing vnitie, to the end al the church might bée edified, as wel by the one as the other, which he hath done quite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary in your confeſſion, as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> words of the .xvij. article in this ſort: <hi rend="italic">Quòd aduerſariorum coena impiè cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bretur. Si quis hactenus dubitauit, vtra ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia ſit verior in ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taria controuerſia, ille ſanè vel ex ſolis ipſoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agendis ac formulis</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9172:49"/> 
               <hi rend="italic">ſacrae communionis, &amp; ipſa praxi coenae ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuere haud difficulter poterit. Tantis enim corruptelis, ſacrilegijs, in ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſacroſanctis my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterijs graſſantur, vt citra horrorem ac tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morem eas prophanationes pia mens cognoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere non poſſit. Eas igitur vastationes ac vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olationes tanti mysterij hic breuiter expone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, vt ſibi puſilli Christi cauere à tantis piaculis &amp; ira Dei poſſint. Multis ergo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis eorum liturgia impiè peragitur.</hi> That is to ſay: If any by the things aforeſayd be yet in doute, not knowing whiche is the trueſt opinion in the matter of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, he may eaſily bée certified of a truth, in beholding their actions and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies <note place="margin">A ſharp poynt of M. Yllyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</note> in the celebration of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion: for there be ſo many corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ſacrileges in ſo holy myſteries, that a Chriſtian mynde can not beholde ſuch prophanations withoute horror and feare. Wée wyll then declare briefly in this Epiſtle, the diſtructions and viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that ar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted in ſo gret a myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end the litle ones of Chryſt may ſtand vppon their garde ageinſt ſuch exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable crimes, but ſpecially ageinſt the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ire
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:9172:49"/> of God. Their ceremonie of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <note place="margin">The preachers of the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpurge accuſe the other mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</note> (that is to ſay, of the ſacramentaries as you call them) is celebrated with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie in many ſorts. Firſt you ſay, that we make no benediction vpon the bread. Secondly, in that, that when we giue the breade, we exhort thoſe that receiue it to haue remembrance of Ieſus Chryſt bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, offred, and ſacrificed for oure recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation to the heuenly father, and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of our ſinnes with the diuine iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. Thirdly, bicauſe that in this, wée ſéeke to be folowers of Ieſus Chriſt, who celebrating the Supper, ſayd to his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: Take and eate. &amp;c. Fourthly, you accuſe vs in that wée forget in the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the words of conſecration. Fifthly, for that wée pronounce not the woordes of conſecration, to the ende the breade may perceiue our voice, with vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the word of God, conuerſion into the body of Chryſte. Sixtely, you accuſe vs bycauſe wée perſuade the aſſiſtantes, not to ſettle their eyes vpon the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the viſible &amp; exterior elements, but rather raiſe our myndes and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb facs="tcp:9172:50"/> to Ieſus Chriſt, the true heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bread for the nouriture of our ſoules, who being alredy immortall, is glorified vpon the right hande of the Father. The ſeuenth impietie which you ſay we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte, is, That wée tell the aſſiſtauntes that they take the breade and Wine in remembraunce of Ieſus Chryſte. In the eyght, you ſay wée fayle, in that wée vſe the woordes of Chryſte, ſaying: Take and eate, and haue remembrance of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chryſte employed for you, wherein according to your ſcoffes of cuſtome and poeticall ſleightes, you make vs like to the <hi rend="roman">Beguiars</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Beguines,</hi> when they féede in their repaſtes. The Lorde par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don you ſuche orders of teaching to your neighboures, and reueale vnto you the modeſt grauitie which he demaundes in thoſe that profeſſe themſelues paſtors of the ſhéepe, and pronouncers of the goſpel. Ninthly, you blame vs in that we do not counterfet Ieſus Chriſt as the prieſts of the Papiſts do, as obſeruing not point by poynt, and worde by worde, the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies that he made, and ſpeake not in the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:9172:50"/> ſame order the words which he pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. Your tenth and laſte accuſation is, in that (as you ſay) we rob deceitfully the ſupper of the wordes of conſecration, by mean wherof the body of Chriſt ought to come thither, and yet we ſay to the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts that they receiue the body of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="77">77 Behold (deare brethren) one part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> accuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wherwith you haue char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vs touching the matter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Supper, whervnto I will not anſwere, as being things ſo vayn &amp; of ſo ſmall importance, that there is none participating with ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pietie or godlineſſe, which acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt not the time loſt, or at leaſt euil employed in the debate of ſuch things, for as the Lord hath made vs once to vnderſtande (by his grace) what it is to receiue Chriſte, and that wée haue felte the frutes of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, ſo all youre accuſations and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentes of perſuaſions to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, are but ſuperfluous. And therefore in place to make you anſwer, and fal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fault which I ſée in many, who do nothing in all the tyme of their lyfe, but diſpute and debate, I will praye to that
<pb facs="tcp:9172:51"/> good God to giue vs all a grace of partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation with his light, whiche chaſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all darkneſſe of errour &amp; ignorance.</p>
            <p n="78">78 I pray you what frute can proceede in writing a new booke of the queſtions and differences, that theſe .xxx. yeares haue bin ſo ſharply argued, and yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out profite. Would it be any other thing than in cauſing to bée reprinted ſundrye repetitions, to fil the faires of <hi rend="italic">Frankefort,</hi> and ſet the bookeprinters on work? A va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie moſte greate, and yet followed of many men of knowledge, who, deſirous by theſe meanes too borrowe themſelues an eſtimation, wiſh that the world knew that they haue ſuch a facilitie to compoſe bookes, that in one euening after ſupper, they can write as many quaires, as may ſuffiſe a ſpedie Printer too imprint in a wéeke. Conſidering (alas) not at all, that the deuotion of a chriſtian conſiſts not in wordes, nor in the multitude of papers &amp; bookes, but in the true feare of God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with liuely faith and carefull mortification, with ſtudy, by all our poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible meanes to preſerue the league of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:9172:51"/> charitie one to an other, giuing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde to knowe, by our lyfe and example, that our confeſſion is the better.</p>
            <p n="79">79 I coulde haue wiſhed (deare bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) that where in your confeſſion, you haue diſgorged ſo many iniuries at your pleaſure, ageynſt ſuche as deſire youre wealth and honour, at the leaſt that you had giuen a ſhew of a chriſtian modeſtie. But it ſéemeth that in this vncharitable ſhewe, you had a deſire to declare an eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent witneſſe of the hate and euill will you beare ageinſt your neighbours, and that without any iuſt occaſion in them: calling them aduerſaries and enimies, profanors of the Supper of the Lord, and darkening with corruption the words of S. Paule. You call them ſacramentors, people that know not what meaneth the aſcention of Chryſte, what is his ryghte hand, nor what is glorification of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie of the Lorde, with other lyke things.</p>
            <p n="80">80 Let vs leaue, let vs leaue (good bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) ſuch maner of diſputation, and let vs forget to mainteine oure owne inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation:
<pb facs="tcp:9172:52"/> yea let vs ſearch the edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the churche of Chryſte, and not our owne glorie. Let vs ſtudie to leade men by our preachings to Ieſus Chriſte our Soueraine Doctour, and not to followe neither the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auſpurge,</hi> the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme of <hi rend="roman">Martine,</hi> nor the interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi rend="roman">Iohn</hi> nor <hi rend="roman">Peter.</hi> Let vs make it knowne to al the princes and potentates of <hi rend="italic">Germanie,</hi> that all thoſe queſtions bée baniſhed, &amp; wée in deſire to liue in recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation and friendſhip: And let not the weake haue occaſion to ſay, that we ſerue moſt as matches &amp; bellows, to kindle the hearts of ſuch perſonages, to make them ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues enimies of thoſe who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe one ſelf Goſpell of Chryſt with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p n="81">81 Truly the doctors, paſtors and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpell, ought to be ſuche now, as by word and writing, to become ſuters to the Princes Proteſtantes, to take into their protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and vnder their wings, the churches which the Lord hath ſtirred vp in theſe lowe Countreys, and that they may become humble interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoures to the king of <hi rend="italic">Spayne,</hi> oure ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:9172:52"/> Magiſtrate, for pitie ouer his poore and moſt loyall ſubiectes, who withoute any offence vnto the maieſtie of theyr Prince, bée perſecuted, murdered, afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as ſeditious and rebells, and hande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with more crueltie than may bée be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeued but of ſuche as haue ſeene it.</p>
            <p n="82">82 In the meane whyle, wee triumph in the chaire, with beſtowyng here and there, captious Inuectyues, callynge ſome Caluiniſtes, ſome Sacramentors, ſome ſeditious and rebelles, breakers of Images with other lyke. Wee ſende oure Confeſſyons ſtuffed wyth Iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous matters, debates, and quarrells, to the Princes of <hi rend="italic">Alm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yn,</hi> to the end they may ſee what valiant champions we are on this ſyde. And howe (at the leaſt) the Confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auspurge</hi> triumpheth in the towne of <hi rend="italic">Antwerpe</hi> by oure meanes. In the whych meane whyle, the glorie of Ieſus Chriſt is buried, or altogither forgotten, and wée haue ſo hardened our harts, that the afflictions of our brethren and neighbours doe not touche vs at all, but we heare them reckened, and recken
<pb facs="tcp:9172:53"/> them our ſelues with ſcoffes and mocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, thinking to eſcape better cheape, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are couered with the confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auſpurge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="83">83 No no (brethren) it can not be ſo, for God knoweth how and where to find vs, though it be in the bottom of the ſea: he hath his armes ſo long, that he is able to drawe vs from the lappe of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Monarchs of the earth. And therfore lette vs not put our truſt in the ſtrength of the fleſh, but rather let vs march with all feare afore GOD, and ſearche only his glorie. And in place to make factions and ſeparations of the churche, let vs go with one courage and heart to batter the kyngdome of Sathan, wyth the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions and idolatries brought into oure chriſtian religion by him and his ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes. Let vs make warre ageynſt vices, and not ageynſt men, which bée the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures <note place="margin">We ought ſo to preach and write ageinſt the abuſe of the papiſts with a chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an modeſty.</note> of God (bée they Papiſts or other) diſcouering ſo the abuſes, as neyther the abuſers nor they that be abuſed thynke, that we crie out ageynſt them rather by iniurious malice, than for a zeale wée
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:9172:53"/> haue to drawe them to one eſtate.</p>
            <p n="84">84 Of what purpoſe is it to vs to fill oure books and writings with iniuries a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geinſt the Pope, Cardinalls, Biſhops, Préeſtes, and Moonkes, and to ſtudie for exquiſite words and infamous epithetes to breath vppon them in the pulpit? Are wée ſo forgetfull that wée remember not what we haue bin our ſelues? Lette vs beare in mynde, that there haue not paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed many yeares ſince wée were in the ſame pitte and quagmier plunged vp to the chinne, yea euen to the top of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, from whence, if the Lord of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe haue drawne vs, diſplaying the tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of his mercy vppon vs, followeth it therefore that we ſhoulde either exclame or cry out ageinſt thoſe as vnhappily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine yet in the place, from whence we are come? Were it not better to offer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oure hand to helpe to pull them out of the pitte, and to exhorte them gently to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the myſerable eſtate wherin they are? for it is impoſſible euer to gain their hearts by the way we take, bycauſe man will be in libertie touchyng his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léefe
<pb facs="tcp:9172:54"/> and religion: and the more he ſhall be reſiſted, the more eiger will he be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the purſute of that that is def<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>too him: employing his bodye and goods, with lyfe and all (if neede be) to preſerue his liberty in theſe poynts, and laſtly wil eſtéeme thoſe, as his ſworne enemies, who by any other meanes (than gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) will ſéeke to ſpoyle him of this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie,</p>
            <p n="85">85 Too this (brethren) you may aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer me, that the tyrannie of the papiſts is ſo abhominable that there is no hart poſſeſſed with any Religion, whoſe paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence may endure ſo intollerable a yoke <note place="margin">The tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nie of the Papiſts vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualtie and temporaltie.</note> into the church of God, ſéeing they ar not contented to bury the benefites of Ieſus Chryſt, to rob and vſurpe his dignitie, to make themſelues merchants of his blud and redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to beguile and ſeduce the poore people and their conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces ſending ſoules to hell, in place to draw them out of purgatorie, and laſtly as a full of their tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nie haue ſubdued and put vnder their féete the Monarchs, Emperours, Kings, Princes, and Magiſtrates of the earth,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:9172:54"/> forcing them to an humilitie vpon their féete: they haue vſurped Seigniories and principalities by violence and effuſion of mans bloud, to the ende to make themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues Princes and great Lordes and their children, neuews, and allies, hauing at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyred themſelues gorgiouſly with ſtolne feathers like to Eſops crow: and where afore they were ſo ſimple, that they had ſcarcely wherewith to fill their bellies, nowe ſome of them are become Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſome Dukes, Earles, Marquiſſes: others triumph at their pleaſure, deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the goodes of ſtraungers: all which is tollerable with them, bycauſe that the Pope their father hath put them in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of ſuche wealth iniuſtly vſurped. And if any one (kindeled with the grace of our Lorde) be priuie to ſuche abuſes, and goeth aboute too diſcouer them too the people, incontinent the Popes, their Parentes and Allies, with open mouth do call ſuche Preachers Heretikes, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtates, banniſhed Strangers and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vnworthye of reléefe in a Common ſtate, and will enter foorthwith into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe
<pb facs="tcp:9172:55"/> and trauaile, and that with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to commit them eyther to the fyre and fagotts, or otherwiſe to extirpe them quite from the earth: bycauſe they feare that the preachers of truth, diſcoueryng their pot of roſes (as the prouerbe ſayth) and that the worlde vnderſtanding their tirannies, euery one will withdraw and take away his fether rightely belonging to him: and ſo in the end, the Crow will eftſoones become a crow, and the ſimple and poore man returne to his firſt eſtate.</p>
            <p n="86">86 Herevnto I aunſwere and ſaye, (good brethren) that you haue greate rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and I woulde in GOD the ſtones had mouthes to manyfeſt ſuche abuſes. But yet ther is neceſſary to our ſide a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber obſeruation of modeſtie in the words we vſe to ſpeake: for my part, I dout not at all, that the diligence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Popes, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, <note place="margin">The cauſe why the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and their allies make warre ageinſt the Goſpel.</note> with their parents and Allies, is not rather to maynteyne their vſurped e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, than the glorie and zeale of God: for if they had any religion, they would ſhew it in their life and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation. But (alas) all the worlde ſéeth that the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:9172:55"/> zealors and defendors of the Papiſts, ſhew almoſt no feare of god: &amp; the Popes themſelues, deride with open throate our Sauior Chryſt, according to the example of one that died not long ſince, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing left behynde him many lordſhips to his children and nephews, vſurped by ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie, ſayd (in ſort of railing or madde ſcoffing) that this fable of Ieſus Chryſt, had greately profited many houſes, who of ſhifting royſters and diſordred people were become poſſeſſoures of large reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues. Marke this blaſphemie, conſider what religion this holy S. Peter and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car of Chriſt hadde in his heart, who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding vſed his tymes and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſo conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, as he forgat nothing that concerned his profite. But my hope is in God, that he wil diſtroy that <hi rend="roman">Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> and the tyrant <hi rend="roman">Nemroth,</hi> that defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth hir, his parents and Allies, who to preſerue their vſurpations, raiſe war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geinſt the children of GOD, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them.</p>
            <p n="87">87 Expectyng (deare brethren) this horrible iudgement and moſt aſſured pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment
<pb facs="tcp:9172:56"/> that will fal vpon them, let vs vſe pacience in the wrong they offer vs: If they call vs heretikes, bicauſe we wil not folow the faith of theyr Popes, but imbrace that which Chryſt hath taught vs. Let vs eſtéeme oure ſelues happie, if they cal vs apoſtates, bicauſe we be come foorth, or rather the Lorde hath wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deliuered vs from the Idolatries and ſuperſtitions of the Papiſtes. Let vs accompt our ſelues neuertheleſſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie: for my part, I proteſt afore the Lord, that it is to mée a title and ſurname of glorie and dignitie, to be called Apoſtate of the Pope and the Antechryſt of <hi rend="italic">Rome.</hi> If they call vs baniſhed from oure coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, let vs rather reioyce than diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, knowing that God hath not bany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed vs from his grace, neyther is it Chriſte that hath throwne vs out of his ſpirituall kingdome: but it is the inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitours, who wold eyther haue baniſhed or burned vs <hi rend="roman">per effigiem,</hi> in performing their rage vppon the ſtrawe and papers, bicauſe they could not execute it vpon the fleſh and bones of the membres of Ieſus
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:9172:56"/> Chriſt, Let vs giue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks to God in that ſuch baniſhments and perſecutions pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede not to vs as being guiltie eyther of theft, murder or treaſon to oure Prince and Magiſtrate, nor atteynted of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offence worthy of puniſhment, but bicauſe we ſearch the health of our ſoules in the ſimple and pure worde of God.</p>
            <p n="88">88 If they call vs ſtraungers, let vs <note place="margin">The children of God are neuer out of their owne countrey.</note> remembre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the heauenly Father, which hath aduowed vs for his children, is lorde of heauen and of earth. And into what part ſo euer we ſhall go, we be in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of our father, we be his propre inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritaunce, as the Prophete ſayeth in the Pſalm. 37. That the rightuous ſhal dwel in the earth, and be lawfull poſſeſſors of the ſame. Lette vs comforte oure ſelues in this, that neyther oure running oute of the countrey, nor oure abſence from the lande of oure birth, hath bin moued by any vſurpation of the poſſeſſions or goodes of other: but onely to giue place to perſecutions. Suche fléeing awaye is not ſhamefull, but rather honourable, ſéeing wée are companyons of our head
<pb facs="tcp:9172:57"/> and redéemer Ieſus Chriſte, who from his childhood was a ſtranger in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys of the Egyptians, ſhewing the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions of <hi rend="roman">Herode.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="89">89 If oure perſecuters do curſe vs, let vs bliſſe them, if they ſearch or ſéeke oure death, let vs pray for their lyfe: And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther ſhal come queſtion to diſcouer their abuſes, tyrannies and extortions, let vs vſe it with ſobrietie, modeſtie, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie, that it may appere eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, that we are not led by any malice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geynſt their perſones, but of a ſpirituall zeale to the glorie of God, the aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the kingdom of Chryſt, chiefe of the church, and to the health of the ſoules of the poore and ſimple people, beguyled and ſeduced euen vntill now, by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of dreames and fables, who vnder the colour of Ieſus Chryſte, haue marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his church: and being in deed very ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening Wolues, doe name themſelues paſtors and ſhepeherdes of the troupe of God. Laſtely, lette vs endeuer to liue in peace one with an other, whether they be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romiſh religion, or reformed church,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:9172:57"/> praying always to the Lorde that he wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lighten vs in oure ignoraunces, whiche wee ought to ſhew to euery one with all modeſtie and gentleneſſe, according too the example of oure maiſter and Redée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ieſus, who hath not diſdained to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue gently, and teache myldely his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Iohn. 3.</hi>
               </note> enemies perſecutyng him dayly, and makyng coniurations to take from hym <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Luke. 7.</hi>
               </note> his life. Let vs remember that being eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon the croſſe, pinched with the extreme pangs of death, not mynding his owne paines, he had remembraunce of his eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, with prayer to his heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to pardon their offences: let vs imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Lorde our creator, whoſe mercy and goodneſſe are ſo plentiful, that he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his ſunne ſhine bothe vpon the good and the euill. Let vs not vſe regarde, that this man hath ſuche an ignoraunce, nor that man will receiue any article of our confeſſion. Let vs loue all, helpe all, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace al, and ſupport the ignorances and infirmities of al. For better were it that we failed in this point (if it be a fault at all) than to make vs iudges of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb facs="tcp:9172:58"/> of an other, and giue out ſentence of condemnation ageinſt thoſe that agrée not with vs.</p>
            <p n="90">90 For ende (deare brethren) I beſech you take in good parte this my epiſtle or letter, mouing no otherwyſe than of an affectioned hart towards you, wherof the Lorde is my witneſſe, and I aſſure it in myne owne conſcience: and let it not (I pray you) be an occaſion to you to write bookes nor Pamphlets, ſéeing I haue no meaning too enter into armes or warre with the pen, neither doth the time ſerue for it, but rather of neede to vs all to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply oure ſelues to better things: and let vs labour to encreaſe oure knowledge in that which we want to be doctors of the goſpel: for the acknowledging of our ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce oughte rather to incenſe vs to a wil to learn, than to make our ſelues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitours and cenſors of the Faythe of others, with employing the time to fill bookes and papers, with queſtions alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither impertinent to edification.</p>
            <p n="91">91 I humbly beſéech the ſoueraine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of our good God &amp; heauenly father,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:9172:58"/> that it will pleaſe him too furniſhe youre iudgements and vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dings with the knowledge of his holy woord, to the ende that by the meane of youre preachings, youre audience may learne a true faithe, an aſſured hope in Ieſus Chryſte, and a carefull mortification of the olde Adam, and that the ſame Lorde, ſo renue youre harts &amp; enflame your wills in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> affection of charitie towards your neibors, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> from hence forth, wée, being ioyned with you, and you with vs, may liue in peace, and tranquilitie of body and ſpirite in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of oure Lorde Ieſus ſoueraigne paſtor of our ſoules, who, hauing bought vs by the ineſtimable price of his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and bloude moſte precious, it may alſo pleaſe hym too garde vs ageynſt all diſſentions, &amp; make vs liue in the vnitie of himſelfe, vntill, that béeing ſpoyled of this corruption, wée may perfectely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in the coniunction of him and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal glorie promiſed vs by his meane, of the which in his own perſon, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rather to make vs inheritors therof, he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redy take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſſeſſion, ſitting on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb facs="tcp:9172:59"/> of God with all power in Heauen and earth. To whome bée all glorie and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire for euer. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>In the towne of Antwerp. <date>ij. of Ianua. 1567.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>Your affectioned brother in Ieſus Chriſt, and humble companion in the work of GOD, Anthonie de Corro, called Belle Riue.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="addendum">
            <head>To the Churche of Antwerpe.</head>
            <p>THis only (deare brethren) was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by this Epiſtle or Sermon, to imparte it by conference with the prechers of the church, naming themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of the confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auspurge,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meaning to communicate it by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication, albeit bycauſe diuers written copies are comen into the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of ſundry and ſeuerall perſons, I thought it to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter purpoſe to ſpread abroad and deliuer it in print, than to ſuffer it to be argued in ſecrete, leaſte the ſame mighte moue
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:9172:59"/> cauſe of ſiniſter iudgement ageinſt the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and ſincere integritie of my meanyng, wherein as the labour was peculiar in my ſelfe, without the enteruiew or counſell of any, ſo, if it include any matter to edifie or confirme your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences, it may pleaſe you to be thankfull to the Lorde as author of al goodneſſe. And for the errors, I beſéech you let them be layde wholly vpon me, as vpon a man, who liuing yet in the peregrination to our heauenly countrey, where (wée ſhall haue perfect knowleage) may erre and faile in many things. For wée know that we are <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">2. Cor. 5.</hi>
               </note> trauailers and iorneymen in this body, we are abſente from the Lorde, and walke by Faith, and not by view. For ende, I wipe my hands afore God and you all of any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent eyther to redarguate or confute the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles preſented by thoſe that call themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of the Confeſſion of <hi rend="italic">Auſpurge,</hi> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to let them ſée vpon what ſmall cauſes they haue formed greate quarels, mayntei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng diſſention for a thing of ſmall impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, and forbeare too deale in matters more neceſſary.</p>
            <p>SEing alſo (good brethren (that vppon the impreſſion there remained certeine lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues
<pb facs="tcp:9172:60"/> voyde and vnfurnyſhed of matter, I thought it not oute of purpoſe to fyll them wyth certeine places of Holie Scripture, perſuading the Faythefull to actes of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, wyth brotherly vnitie one to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yea not to forbeare to loue oure pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per enemies, and ſuche as purſue vs with perſecution: a vertue at this day, moſte im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portaunt and neceſſary, the rather for that Sathan employeth a wonderfull diligence to ſowe ſéedes of diſſention and quarrell, with ſpeciall endeuour and ſtrange mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes too corrupt the league of charitie lefte vnto vs by Chryſte of ſuche commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and all thys vnder a pretence of diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie in religion, wherein as wée oughte to ſtand vppon our garde ageinſt the ſubtilties and policies of the Diuel, ſo aſſuredly, God hath not lefte vs eyther lycence or lybertie once to thinke, that it is lawfull for vs to hate any man, in reſpect to maynteine our religion, ſéeing wée are expreſly enioyned by the wordes of the ſame, to loue ſuche as deſpiſe vs, and pray for thoſe that perſecute oure bodies and doings. But alas, wée are ſlipte into a time ſo miſerable, and infected with ſuch corruption and blindneſſe, that in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:9172:60"/> the maynteyning of the integritie of oure faith, we become preiuditiall to the league of charitie, with a negligent care of the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the ſame. For my part I allow iuſtly ſuch diligence as is vſed in the purgation of abuſes and errors, to the end our holy faith and Religion may the rather be purifyed, and remayne without ſpot: albéeit I wiſhe a precyſe obſeruation of Chriſtian chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, leaſt in making warre ageynſt the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes of oure fayth, wée become not he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes ageynſt charitie. For which cauſe and to the ende that euery one be priuie to the bond and obligation which God in this purpoſe, demaundes at our handes, I haue heere coolled oute of the diuine worde cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine ſpeciall Textes importing oure cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable dueties and office vnto oure neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure, deſiring you (deare brethren) to conſtrue in the beſte my intente, tending ſimply and altogither to refute thoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, dreames, and errours, whiche I ſée ſundry with no ſmal diligence, labor to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and mainteyne in the church of Chriſt wiſhing they participated rather with a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite of humilitie and mildeneſſe in the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the opynions of others, than to
<pb facs="tcp:9172:61"/> ſtryue to become inquiſitors of other mens faith, and much leſſe to enter into ſentence of iudgement ageynſt ſuche as refuſe their interpretations, vntil they be aſſured by the ſpirit of God, that ſuch opinions are direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ageynſt the heauenly word, and that we haue witneſſe in our conſcience, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs to do it, for then he himſelf wil cloth vs with the affection of his apoſtle, who to gaine and reduce his brethren woulde not ſticke almoſt to abandon his propre health: euen ſo when wée féele ſuche a zeale moue <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Rom. 9.</hi>
               </note> in vs, euen then alſo ſhall we proue in our ſelues, that God will bliſſe our enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Let vs then embrace peace, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine mutuall accord, ſéeing that as there is nothyng that leuieth a more ſharpe warre within vs, than our owne diſcordes, diſdai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and partialities, ſo of the contrarie, if we marche vnder the enſigne of charitie, ſupporting one an other in our infirmities, it ſhall bée moſt harde eyther to breake our aray, or put vs to flighte: For as <hi rend="roman">Salomon</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Eccl. 4.</hi>
               </note> ſayth: The accorde of thrée ſtrings is very harde to breake.</p>
            <p>My litle childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I am yet for a litle time with you, you ſhall ſearch me, but as I ſayd <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Iohn. 13.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:9172:61"/> to the Iews, that whether I go, they could not come, I ſay alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame vnto you nowe, giuing you this new commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement, that you loue one an other (as I ſay) I haue lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued you, to the ende alſo that you loue one an other. By this all men ſhall know, that you are my diſciples, if you loue one an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. That is the principall marke of oure chriſtianitie, all others that wée maye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, may be folowed of the hypocrites, but this is inimitable, bicauſe it is peculiar on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the regenerate, and thoſe that bée re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued by the ſpirite of God.</p>
            <p>Bée you deſirous of the moſte exellent <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Cor. 12. &amp; 13.</hi>
               </note> giftes, and I wil ſhew you a way yet more excellent. If I ſpeke the languages of men and Angels, and haue not Charitie, I am as the mettall that ſoundes, or Cimball that tynkes. And if I haue the gifte of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie, and knowe all ſecretes, and euery ſcience, and if I had ſuche faith as I might tranſporte the mountaynes, and haue not charitie, I am nothyng: if I diſtribute all my goodes to the reléefe of the poore, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer my body to be burned, and haue not charitie, it profiteth me nothyng: Charitie is not eaſily incenſed to anger, but ſhée is
<pb facs="tcp:9172:62"/> mylde. Charitie is not enuious, Charitie is not inſolente, ſhe ſwelleth not with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſhe dothe not vſe hir ſelfe diſhoneſtly, ſhe ſearcheth not hir profite, ſhe is not deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pytefull, ſhe thinkes no euill: Shée taketh no pleaſure in iniuſtice, but reioyceth in the truthe: ſhée endureth all, beléeueth all, hopeth for all, and ſuffereth all: Charitie neuer falleth. And a little after he ſayeth: Theſe thrée thyngs remaine, Fayth, Hope, and Charitie: wherof the greateſt is Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. Thoſe bée the effectes of Chriſtian Charitie, whyche is neyther vayne opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyon nor curteſye in outwarde ſhewe, but rather a vertue bryngyng foorth wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full frutes.</p>
            <p>Touchyng brotherly Charitie, there is <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">1. Teſſa. 4.</hi>
               </note> no great néede I write to you therof, ſeing you are taughte of GOD to loue one an other, for euen ſo you do towardes all your brethren whiche bée in <hi rend="italic">Macedonie.</hi> Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, we exhorte you to ſurmounte more and more with diligence to liue peaceably: If the vnction of the Spirite of God haue not yet taught you to loue your neighbors, let vs feare that our doctrine is not rather learned of men, than in the ſchoole of God.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:9172:62"/>
            <p> He that ſayeth he is in the light, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his brother, is in darknes to this hour: <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">1. Iohn. 2. &amp;. 3.</hi>
               </note> who loueth his brother, remayneth in the light, and falles not: but he that hateth his brother walketh in darkeneſſe, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not whether he goeth, for the darkeneſſe hath blinded his eyes. By this are manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the children of God, and the children of the diuell. Who ſo euer dothe not iuſtice, and loueth not his brother is not of God: for this is it you haue heard preached from the beginning, that wée loue one an other, not as Cain, which was called wicked, and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his brother: and for what cauſe did he kil him? for that his woorks were wicked, and his brothers were iuſt. Brethren marueile not if your brother hate you: in that we loue our brethren, we know we are tranſferred from death to life: who loueth not his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dwelleth in death: who hateth his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is a murderer. And you know that no murderer hath eternal life remaining with in him: by this we know his charitie, that he hath giuen his lyfe for vs, we ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to hazard our liues for our brethren. And this is a moſt certeine and ample explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the marke of oure chriſtianitie which
<pb facs="tcp:9172:63"/> may ſerue as a touche ſtone to aſſure vs of our adoption.</p>
            <p>Hate maketh quarels, but charitie coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Prouerb 10. Verſ. 12.</hi>
               </note> al grudges. This witneſſe doth teache vs that the roote of diſſentions &amp; debates, is the default of chriſtian charitie, which doth not only couer outward ſinnes, but alſo the ignorances of the vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>The furious ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moueth contention, but <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Ibidem. 15. Verſe. 17. &amp; 18.</hi>
               </note> the pacient man appaiſeth quarell: this is a looking glaſſe wherin wée may behold the troubleſome mynds of our tyme, who vpon ſmall cauſes will ſtirre vp ſtrange quarels and debates.</p>
            <p>Welbéeloued, let vs loue one an other, <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">1. Iohn.</hi>
               </note> for charitye is of God, and who loueth, is borne of God, and knoweth God, and hée that loueth not, knoweth not God, for God is charitie. In this is manifeſted the chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of God towards vs, that he hath ſent his only ſon intoo the world, to the end we may liue by him. In this is charitie, not that wée haue loued God, but bycauſe he hath loued vs, and ſent his ſon to bée the appointment for oure ſinnes: Welbeloued, if God haue ſo loued vs, we ought alſo to loue one an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Neuer any man hath ſene God. If we
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:9172:63"/> loue one an other, God dwelleth in vs, and his charitie is accompliſhed in vs: by this we know that we dwell in him, &amp; he in vs, that he hath giuen vs of his holy ſpirit. And a litle after: If any ſay that he loueth God, and hateth his brother, he is a lyer: for if he loue not his brother whome he ſéeth, howe can he loue God whome he ſéeth not? And we haue this commaundement of him, that he that loueth God, loueth alſo his brother. This text hath no nede of interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but rather of proofe and examination, wherein let euery man ſounde and proue his heart, whether theſe woordes be with hym or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geynſt him.</p>
            <p>Thou ſhalte not ſée the Oxe or ſhéepe of <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Deut. 22.</hi>
               </note> thy brother ſtrayed out of the way, &amp; hide thée from them, but thou ſhalt bring them ageyn to thy brother. And if thy brother be not thy neyghboure, and thou knowe hym not, then ſhalt thou leade them within thy houſe, and ſuffer them to remain with thée vntill thy brother demaund them, and then thou ſhalt reſtore them to hym: thou ſhalt doo in lyke manner to his Aſſe, to his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and al the loſt things of thy brother, which he hath loſt and thou founde, neither
<pb facs="tcp:9172:64"/> muſt thou hyde them: thou ſhalt not ſée the Aſſe or Ox of thy brother falne in the way, and hide thée from them, but thou ſhalte helpe to lift them vp with him. If the Lord commaunde that our charitie be ſhewed in the lifting vp of beaſts, let vs conſider with ſtronger reaſon, that his maieſtie woulde that we haue care of the ſoules of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren &amp; neighbors: whom if we ſée ſtrayed from the way of truth, let vs labour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them: if they be falne into the pit of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, let vs offer them our hands rather than to pronounce ſentence of condemnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and purſue them euen vnto death.</p>
            <div type="Scripture_passages">
               <head>Texts of the diuine worde, exhorting vs to loue oure enimies, and pray for ſuch as perſecute vs.</head>
               <p>Thou ſhalt not walke as a detractour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt <note place="margin">
                     <hi rend="roman">Leui. 19.</hi>
                  </note> the people, thou ſhalte not dreſſe thy ſelfe ageynſt the bloud of thy neyghbor, for I am the Lord: Thou ſhalt not hate thy brother in thy heart, correct thy neighbour, and ſuffer no ſynne vpon him: Thou ſhalt not reuenge nor kéepe malice ageynſt the children of thy people: but thou ſhalt loue thy neighbor as thy ſelf: for Iam the Lord.</p>
               <p>You haue heard that it hath bin ſaid, thou <note place="margin">
                     <hi rend="roman">Math. 5.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:9172:64"/> ſhalt loue thy neyghbour, and hate thy eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. But I ſay vntoo you: Loue youre eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, bliſſe thoſe which curſe you, do good to ſuche as hate you, and pray for thoſe that runne vppon you to perſecute you, to the ende you be the children of your father that is in heauen: for hée maketh his Sun ſhyne vppon the good and euill, and ſendes rayne vppon the iuſt and iniuſt: For if yée loue thoſe that loue you, what reward haue you therefore? The Paganes doe not they the like alſo? And if you imbrace onely youre brethren, what do you more? Do not the pagans alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like? Be you perfect as youre father is perfect that is in heauen.</p>
               <p>Do not render to any euill for euil: pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure <note place="margin">
                     <hi rend="roman">Rom. 12.</hi>
                  </note> honeſt things afore all men: And if it may be at leaſt as muche as is in you, haue peace with al men. Do not reuenge (welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) but giue place to anger, for it is wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: To me belongeth vengeance, ſayth the Lord, and I will giue it: if then thy enimy bée hungrie, giue him too eate, if hée haue thirſt, giue him to drinke: for in this doing thou ſhalte aſſemble coales of fier vpon his head. Be not ouercome with euill, but ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount the euill by the good.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9172:65"/>
               <p> Owe nothing to any man, if not that you <note place="margin">
                     <hi rend="roman">Rom. 13.</hi>
                  </note> loue one an other: for who loueth an other hath accompliſhed the lawe, whiche ſayth: Thou ſhalt not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit adultery, thou ſhalt not kil, thou ſhalt beare no falſe witneſſe, thou ſhalt not couet &amp;c. And if there be any other commaundement, it is in effect com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in this word, Thou ſhalt loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe. Truly if we had this ſtone of foundation of brotherly charitie in the buildings of oure life, trafficks and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts with oure neighbours, all the partes of this ſpirituall houſe which God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs incharge, ſhould be wel ordred and couched.</p>
               <p>After the Lord hadde waſhed their féete, <note place="margin">
                     <hi rend="roman">Iohn. 13.</hi>
                  </note> and taken ageine his garment, and that he was ſet ageine at the table, hée ſayed vntoo them: Know you what I haue done vntoo you? you cal me Lord and maiſter, and you ſay wel, for ſo I am: if then I that am Lord and maiſter haue waſhed youre féete: you ought alſo to waſh one an others féet. For I haue gyuen you example, that euen as I haue done, you may alſo do. Why haue not wée remembraunce of this holy ceremonie when wée celebrate the Supper of Chryſte,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:9172:65"/> ſéeing that hée himſelfe hathe prepared the harts of his diſciples with this admonition afore he ſhewed or did inſtitute the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their coniunction with him, giuing them to vnderſtande that he is not worthy to receiue Ieſus Chryſt, which doth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plye his hart too waſhe the féete of his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren?</p>
               <p>I ſpeake truth in Chryſte, I lye not, my conſcience bearing me witneſſe by the holy <note place="margin">
                     <hi rend="roman">Rom. 9.</hi>
                  </note> ſpirit, that I haue greate ſorow and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall torment in my heart: for I did deſire to be ſeparated with Chriſt for my brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which be my parents according to the fleſh. When we ſhal féele our hearts ſo wel tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with the ſpirit of god, as S. Paul was, let vs ſet vpon hardly to correct the errours and opinions of others, and ſo long as wée are fleſhely, and guided rather by ſtomacke than ſpirituall zele, let vs employ our tyme to pray to God for the ignorant.</p>
               <p>Let vs be then (as choſen veſſels of God, <note place="margin">
                     <hi rend="roman">Coloſſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> holy and welbeloued) clad in the intrails of mercy, humilitie, ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tleneſſe, and of a mynd of pacience, ſupporting one an other, and pardoning one an other if we haue quarel: as Ieſus Chriſt hath pardoned you, euen ſo
<pb facs="tcp:9172:66"/> forgiue you others: and beſides all this, bée attired with charitie, the very bond of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. And let the peace of God gouerne in your harts, whereunto you are all called in one body, and bée gracious. The word of God dwell frutefully in you in all wiſdom, teaching and warning one an other, in Pſalmes, ſongs, and ſpiritual praiſes with grace, ſingyng with youre hart to the Lorde, whereby we ſhall ſée how farre from theſe rules of charitie be they, that in place to edifie the Church of Chryſte, doe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther procure hir con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion with their Debates and queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9172:66"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
